<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antisixtus An oration of Pope Sixtus the fift, vppon the death of the late French King, Henrie the third. With a confutation vpon the sayd oration, wherein all the treacherous practises of the house of Lorraine, are largely described and layde open vnto the view of the world, with a briefe declaration of the kings death, and of many other things worthy the noting, which neuer yet came to light before. Translated out of Latin by A.P.</title>
            <author>Hurault, Michel, d. 1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849467</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849467</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14615</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14615)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 571:08, 1384:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antisixtus An oration of Pope Sixtus the fift, vppon the death of the late French King, Henrie the third. With a confutation vpon the sayd oration, wherein all the treacherous practises of the house of Lorraine, are largely described and layde open vnto the view of the world, with a briefe declaration of the kings death, and of many other things worthy the noting, which neuer yet came to light before. Translated out of Latin by A.P.</title>
                  <author>Hurault, Michel, d. 1592.</author>
                  <author>Sixtus V, Pope, 1520-1590. De Henrici Tertii morte sermo. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts. Part 1 is a translation of a 2 September 1589 oration by Pope Sixtus V upon the death of King Henry III, his "De Henrici Tertii morte sermo". Part 2, the "Antisixtus", which is anonymous, is a translation of a confutation of part 1. Part 2 authorship given to Hurault by STC. The translator's name is unknown.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 22591.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 14001 on UMI microfilm, reel 571.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (part 1 only) and in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 571 (part 1 only, British Library copy) and at reel 1384 (Cambridge University copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  III, --  King of France, 1551-1589 --  Assassination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sixtus --  V, --  Pope, 1520-1590. --  De Henrici Tertii morte sermo --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14615:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14615:1"/>
            <p>ANTISIXTVS. An oration of Pope Sixtus the fift, vppon the death of the late French King, Henrie the third. WITH A Confutation vpon the ſayd <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein all the treacherous practiſes of the</hi> houſe of Lorraine, are largely deſcribed and layde open vnto the view of the world, with a briefe declaration of the Kings death, and of many other things worthy the noting, which neuer yet came to light before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Latin by</hi> A. P.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:14615:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14615:2"/>
            <head>An Oration of Pope Sixtus the fift vpon the death of King Henry the third, in Rome in the full aſſemblie of the Cardinalles.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering oftentimes with my ſelfe, and applying my whole vnderſtanding vnto theſe things, which now of late by a iuſt iudgement of God, are come to paſſe: I thinke I may with right vſe the words of the Prophet Abacuck ſaying: <hi>I haue wrought a worke in your daies, and none will beleeue it, though it be told them.</hi> The French King is ſlaine by the hands of a Friar, for vnto this it may fitly be compared, although the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpake of an other thing, namely of the incarnation of our Lord, which excéedeth and ſurmounteth all other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and miracles whatſoeuer: as alſo the Apoſtle S. Paul referreth the ſame wordes vnto the reſurrection of Chriſt. When the Prophet ſayde <hi>a worke,</hi> his minde was not to ſignifie by it ſome common or ordinarie thing, but a rare and notable matter, and a déede worthie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, as that of the creation of the worlde, The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are the workes of thine handes: And againe, He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſeauenth day, of all the workes which he had made. When he ſayth, <hi>I haue wrought,</hi> with theſe wordes the holy Scripture is wont to expreſſe thinges not come to paſſe by caſualtie, fortune, or accident, but things befallen by the determined prouidence, will, and ordinance of God, as our Sauiour ſayde: The workes which I doe, yée ſhall doe alſo, and yet greater, and many more ſuch like where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the holy Scriptures are repleniſhed. And that he ſaith that it is done in times paſt, herein hee followeth the vſe and order of the other Prophets, who for the certentie of the euent are wont to propheſie of things to come as if they were paſt alreadie. For the Philoſophers ſay, that things
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14615:3"/>paſt are of neceſſitie, things preſent, of being: and thinges to come only of poſſibilitie. For which certaintie the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Iſaie long before prophiſying of the death of Chriſt, hath thus ſpoken: He was led as a ſhéepe to the ſlaughter, and like a dumme lambe before his ſhearer, ſo opened hée not his mouth, &amp;c. And this whereof we ſpeake at this preſent, and which is come to paſſe in theſe our dayes, is a famous, notable, and an vncredible thing not done or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheiued without the particular prouidence and diſpoſition of the Almightie. A Friar hath kilde a King, not a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one, or drawen vpon a péece of paper, or pictured vpon a wall, but the King of France, in the mideſt of his armie, compaſſed and enuiconed round about with his Guard and Souldiers: which truely is ſuch an act, and donne in ſuch a manner, that none will beléeue it, when it ſhall be tolde them, and perhaps our poſteritie and the age to come will account and eſtéeme it but a fable.</p>
            <p>That the king is dead or elſe ſlaine, it is eaſily to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued, but that he is kild and taken away in this ſort, is hardly to be credited, euen as we preſently agrée vnto this that Chriſt is borne of a woman, but if we adde vnto it of a woman virgine, then following naturall reaſon we can in no wiſe aſſent vnto it. Euen ſo we lightly beléeue that Chriſt died, but that he is riſen vp againe from death to life, it falleth harde vnto mans vnderſtanding, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not lightly digeſted. That one is wakened againe out of a ſléepe, extaſie, or a ſound, becauſe it is not againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we naturally beléeue it, but to be riſen againe from death, it ſéemeth ſo vncredible vnto the fleſh, that S. Paule deſputing in Athens of this point, was nuſhked greatly, and accuſed to be a ſetter ſoorth of new Gods, ſo that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (as S. Luke witneſſeth) did mocke him, and many for the ſtrangeneſſe of the doctrine ſaide, We will heare thée againe of this thing. Of ſuch things therefore which befall not, according to the lawes of nature, and the ordinarie courſe thereof, ſpeaketh the Prophet, That none ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue it when it ſhall be tolde them. But wee giue credite
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14615:3"/>vnto it by conſideration of the omnipotencie of God, and by ſubmiſſion of our vnderſtanding vnder the obedience of faith, and ſeruice which we owe vnto our Sauiour Chriſt. And by theſe meanes this that was incredible by nature, commeth credible by faith: therefore we that beléeue not after the fleſh that Chriſt is borne of a virgine, yet when there is added vnto it, that this was doone ſupernaturally by operation of the holy Ghoſt: then truely we agree vnto it, and faithfully beléeue it. So likewiſe when it is ſaide that Chriſt is riſen againe from the dead, as wee are fleſh onely we beléeue it not, but when it is affirmed that this was done by the power of the diuine nature which in him was, then without any doubting we beléeue it. In the ſame manner when it ſhall be tolde vs that ſuch a mightie King was kilde by a poore, ſimple, and a weake Friar, euen in the middeſt of his arnne, and enuironed with his Guardo and Souldiers, to our naturall reaſon and fleſhly capacitie it will ſéeme vncredible, yet conſidering on the other ſide the great and grieuous ſinnes of this King, and the ſpeciall prouidence of the almightie herein, and by what accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and wonderfull meanes he hath accompliſhed his moſt iuſt will and iudgement againſt him, then moſt firmely we will beléeue it. Therefore this great &amp; miraculous worke I may but onely aſcribe it vnto the particular prouidence of God, not as thoſe that referre all things amiſſe vnto ſome ordinarie cauſes, or vnto fortune, or ſuch like acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie euentes, but as thoſe who (more néere obſeruing and looking in the courſe of the whole matter) eaſely ſée that here in this befell many things, which could in no wiſe haue béene brought to paſſe and diſpatched without the ſpeciall helpe of God. And truely the ſtate of Kings and kingdoms and all other ſuch rare and weightie affaires ſhould not be thought to be gouerned of God raſhly and vnaduiſedly. In the holy Scripture ſome are of this kind, and none of them can be referred vnto any other thing, but vnto God the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly author therof: yet there are none wherein the celeſtiall operation more appeareth then in this whereof we ſpeake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14615:4"/>at this preſent. We read in the firſt booke of the Machab. the 6. chap. how Eleazar offered himſelfe vnto a certaine death to kill the king that was an enemie and perſecutor of the people and children of God. For in the battell eſpying an Eliphant more excellent then any of the other beaſtes, whereupon it was like that the king was with a ſwift courſe caſting himſelfe in the middeſt of the troupes of his enemies, here and there making a way perforce, came to the beaſt at laſt, and went vnder her, and thruſt his ſword in her belly and ſlewe her, who falling with the great waight of her bodie preſt him to death, and kilde him out of hande. Here in this we ſée ſome thinges not vnlike vnto ours, as much as toucheth the zeale, vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antneſſe of minde, and the iſſue of the enterpriſe, yet in the reſt there is no compariſon to bée made. Elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus was a Souldier, exerciſed in weapons, and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in warres, ſet in battell, embouldened with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and inflamed with rage and anger: this a Friar not in-ured to the fight, and ſo abhorring of bloud by the order of his profeſſion, that perhappes hee could not abide the cutting of a vaine. He knew the kinde of his death, as alſo the place of his buriall, namely that he ſhould be intombed vnder the fall of the beaſt, and ſo buried in the middeſt of his triumph and victorie. This man did looke for death onely, and expected nothing but vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and moſt cruell torments, and did not doubt before, but that he ſhould lacke a graue to reſt within. But in this are yet many other thinges that can ſuffer no compariſon. The famous hiſtorie of the holy woman Iudith is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently knowen, who tooke counſell with her ſelfe, that ſhée might deliuer her Citie and the people of God (no doubt by the inſpiration of the holy ghoſt) to murther Holophernes chiefe Captaine and Prince of the enemies forces, which ſhe alſo moſt valiantly accompliſhed. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in although appeare many and moſt manifeſt tokens of heauenly direction, yet farre greater argumentes of Gods prouidence, are to be ſéene in the killing of this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14615:4"/>king, and the deliuering of the Citie of Paris, farre more difficult and harder to be brought to paſſe, then was the enterpriſe of Iudith, for this holy woman diſcloſed part of her intention before vnto the Gouernours of the Citie, and went not without great commendation of young and olde, through the gates of Bethalia, and by the watch, in ſight and preſence of the Elders, and Princes of that place: and by that meanes was not ſubiect vnto their exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and ſearching which is alwayes vſed ſo ſtrictly in time of ſiedge and warre, that a flie can hardly without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining get by. She being come to the enemie, through whoſe campe and watches ſhe was to goe, and now often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times examined and ſearched, being a woman, carrying no letters nor weapons about her, from whence any ſuſpition might grow, &amp; yéelding probable reaſons of her comming there, and abandoning of her countrie, was eaſely diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. As alſo for the ſame cauſes, &amp; for her ſexe and exquiſite beautie being brought before this lewd Prince whom luſt, wine, &amp; good chéere had rockt a ſléepe, might lightly perform that which ſhe had determined before. But this religious man had vndertaken a matter of greater waight, and alſo performde it, which was compaſſed with ſo many impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, difficulties &amp; dangers, that it by no earthly meanes could haue béene brought to paſſe without the manifeſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, &amp; ſpeciall ayde of the almightie. Firſt letters of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation were to be procured from the enemie, then was he conſtrained to goe through that gate of the Citie, which directly went to the enemies campe, the which without doubt was ſo narrowly kept and watched in the extremitie of that ſiedge, that euery trifle bred ſuſpition, &amp; none were ſuffred to go forth without curious ſearching before, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their letters, buſines, and affaires they had. But he (a wonderfull thing) went by the watch vnexamined, yea with letters of commendation vnto the enemie, which if they had béene intercepted by the Citizens, without delay &amp; further ſentence he ſhould haue béene executed preſently, &amp; therfore this is a manifeſt argument of Gods prouidence.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14615:5"/>
            <p>But this is a far greater miracle, that he without ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching went alſo through the ennemies campe, by diuerſe watches and ſentinelles, and, which more is, through the garde of the Kings body, and finally, through the whole army, which was compacted almoſt of none but Huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes and Heretickes, he being a religious man, and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled after the order of his profeſſion, which was ſo odions vnto them, that they killed, or at leaſt greatly miſuſed all thoſe friars, whome they found in thoſe places, which not long before they had taken perforce about Paris. Iudith was a woman, and nothing odious, yet examined often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, ſhe carried nothing about her that might haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to her danger or deſtruction. This man, a friar, and therefore hated, and moſt ſuſpected, hauing alſo a knife pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for that purpoſe, not put vp in a ſheath, (which might haue made his excuſation probable) but bare and hidden in his ſléeue, which if it had bene found about him, preſently without any further iudgement ſhoulde haue béene hanged. All theſe are ſuch cleare arguments of the particular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, that they cannot be denied or diſprooued: and it coulde not be otherwiſe, but that God blinded the eies of the ennemies, ſo that they could not ſée nor knowe him. For as we haue ſaid before, although ſome abſurdly aſcribe this vnto fortune, or vnto ſome other ſuch like accident, yet wée thinke good to referre all this to none elſe, but vnto the holy will and ordinance of God. And truely I coulde not beléeue this to haue bene done otherwiſe, vnleſſe I ſhoulde captiue and ſubmit my vnderſtanding vnder the obedience of Chriſt his doctrine, who had determined by theſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous meanes to vnſet and deliuer the city of Paris (which as we haue heard hath béene in great daunger and extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) and iuſtly puniſh the hainous and notorious ſinnes of that king, and take him away out of this worlde by ſuch an vnhappie and infamous death. And we truely (not without great inward griefe) haue oftentimes foretold, that as he was the laſt of his name and familie, ſo was he like to haue, and make ſome ſtrange and ſhamefull ende of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14615:5"/>life. Which, that I haue oftentimes ſaid it, not onely the Cardinalles <hi>Ioioſa, Lenocurtins,</hi> and he of Paris, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Oratour at that time here reſident, can ſufficientlie witneſſe and teſtifie. We will not ſéeme to call here to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our wordes, for thoſe that are already deceaſſed, but the liuing, and ſome of them at this time preſent do yet wel remember them: yet notwithſtanding we will not vnrippe all that we are able and forced to ſpeake againſt this vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate king, for the moſt noble realme of Fraunce it ſake, which we ſhall proſecute and foſter hereafter, as wée haue doone alwayes before with all fatherly loue, honour, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. This therefore which we with griefe haue ſpoken toucheth onely the kinges perſon, whoſe vnhappie and vnluckie ende depriueth and exempteth him alſo of thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and honours which this holie ſea (the tender and gentle mother of all faithfull, but chiefly of chriſtian Princes) is wont to offer vnto all Kinges and Emperours, which wee moſt willingly would likewiſe haue beſtowed vpon him, if the holy ſcriptures in this caſe had not altogether forbidden it. There is, ſaith S. Iohn, a ſin vnto death; I ſay not that any ſhould pray for it, which may be vnderſtoode, both of the ſin it ſelfe, as if he ſhoulde ſay, for that ſin or for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or forgiuenes therof, I will that none ſhould pray, becauſe it is not pardonable. Or elſe in the ſame ſenſe, for that man who committeth ſuch a ſin vnto death, I ſay not that any ſhould pray for. Whereof our Sauiour himſelfe hath ſpoken in S. Mathew, ſaying, that he that ſinneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holie Ghoſt, ſhal not be pardoned, neither in this worlde, nor in the world to come. Where he ſetteth downe thrée ſorts or kindes of ſinne, to wit, againſt the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt, and that the two firſt are leſſe hainous, and pardonable, but that the third is altogether vnpardonable, and not to be remitted. Al which difference procéedeth from the deſtinction of the attributes, as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines teach vs, which ſeuerally are appropriated vnto euery ſeuerall perſon of the holy Trinitie. And although as the eſſence of all the thrée perſons is but one, ſo alſo is their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14615:6"/>wiſedome and goodnes, as we haue learned in the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of Athanaſius, where he ſaith, almighty is the father, almighty is the Sonne, and almighty is the holy Ghoſt: yet by attribution, power is aſcribed vnto the Father, wiſedome vnto the Sonne, and loue vnto the holie Ghoſt, whereof euery ſeuerall as they are tearmed attributes, ſo are they ſo proper vnto euery ſeuerall perſon, that they can not be attributed and referred vnto any other. By the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries of which attributes, we come to diſcerne the diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and greatnes of ſinne. The contrary to power, which is onely attributed vnto the Father, is weaknes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which we doe amiſſe, through infirmity of nature, is ſaid to be committed againſt the Father. The oppoſite vnto wiſdome, is ignorance and blindnes, through which, when any man ſinneth, is ſaid to ſinne againſt the Sonne, therefore that which we commit through naturall infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ignorance, is more eaſier forgiuen vs. The thirds attribute, which is the holy Ghoſtes, is loue, &amp; hath for his contrary ingratitude, and vnthankefulnes, a vice moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and odious, which cauſeth men not to acknowledge the loue of God, and his benefites beſtowed vpon them, but to forget, deſpiſe, yea and to hate them. Whereout brieflie, and finally procéedeth, that they become altogether obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and impenitent. And this way ſinne is committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God with greater danger and perill, then if it were done through ignorance and weakeneſſe of the fleſh, and therfore it is termed, a ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch ſinnes are ſeldome and difficultly pardoned, and not without great aboundance of grace, in ſome ſorte they are ſaid to bee vnpardonable: whereas altogether through vnrepentance only, they become ſimply vnpardonable. For whatſoeuer is done amiſſe in this life: although it be againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, by repentance it may be wipt out &amp; defaced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death, but they that perſeuere therin til death, are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from all grace &amp; mercy hereafter. And therefore for ſuch ſinners and ſinnes the apoſtle hath forbidden to pray after their deceaſe. Now therefore becauſe wée vnderſtand, not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14615:6"/>without our great griefe, that the ſaide king is departed out of this worlde, without repentance and impenitent, in the company, to wit, of heretickes, (for all his army was made almoſt of none other but of ſuch men) and that by his laſt wil he hath commended and committed his crowne and kingdome to the ſucceſſion of Nauarre, long ſince declared an hereticke, and excommunicated, as alſo in his extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and nowe ready to yéelde vp his ghoſt, deſired of him, and ſuch like as he was there ſtanding by, that they would reuenge his death vppon thoſe whome hee iudged to be the cauſe thereof. For theſe and ſuch like moſt manifeſt tokens of vnrepentance, we haue decréed not to ſolemnize his death with funeralles, not that we would ſéeme to coniecture by theſe any thing concerning the ſecrete iudgementes of God againſt him or his mercies, who could according vnto his good pleaſure in the departing of his ſoule from the body co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert and turne his heart, and deale wyth him mercifully: but this we haue ſpoken, being thereunto mooued by theſe externall ſignes and tokens. God grant therefore that all, being admoniſhed and warned by this fearefull example of heauenly iuſtice, may repent and amende, and that it may further pleaſe him to continue and accompliſh that which he hath mercifully begunne in us, as we do put our truſt in him, to the end we may giue euerlaſting thanks to him, to haue deliuered his church from ſuch great &amp; imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Wherof when his holines had ſpoken, he brake vp the Conſiſtorie, &amp; hauing giuen his bleſſing, let them al depart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>ANTISIXTVS.</head>
            <p>THe ages paſt haue ſéene many that vnnaturally haue rebelled againſt their country, and with viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce defiled their hands with the blood of their princes and parents: but none yet that euer approoued or commended the facte. But nowe of late, and in our dayes a notorious murtherer is come forth, the B. of Rome knoweth the cruell and bloody crime, and reprooueth not the offendor, but prayſeth him. This therefore is falſe, <hi>Sixtus,</hi> although it bée an oldé
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14615:7"/>ſaying, that villanie and miſchiefe is more eaſier committed then excuſed: whether I compare thée with Papinian, or rather with Caracalla, both notable tyrantes, yet it will holde in none of them both. With right then may I ſaye with thée, <hi>fact um eſt opus in diebus nostris,</hi> there is wroght a worke in our dayes, to the eye and eare moſt deteſtable and gréeuous, and horrible to be remembred and ſpoken of. The greateſt and mightieſt king of Europe lieth ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and ſlaine by the treacherous fraude of a friar. But dooſt thou tearme this a worke onely? Nay, rather thou ſhouldeſt haue called it a moſt hainous, execrable, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell act: and therefore the more hainous, that not one of the common people, but thou the ruler of chriſtendome, Chriſt his vicar, the gate of heauen, haſt bene the aduocate, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and commender of this great offence. Truely, who can ſuffer the hands of prieſts, which by their laws ſhould be harmeleſſe, and vndefiled of all chriſten blood, although moſt guilty, to be embrued and ſtayned wyth the blood of a prince? Who ſhould not curſe and deteſt the bloody butchar of the father of his country? Haue not the incenſed and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie people, reaſon then to crie, torture, torture, and all things elſe wherewith ſuch cruell monſters are to bée puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed? Yet this is but ſmall, <hi>Sixtus,</hi> and that which thou thinkeſt to be the greateſt part of this villanous acte, is the leaſt. Thou wyth it onely art to be charged, becauſe thou alone art ſounde that commendeſt priuſe murtherers, and praiſeſt manſlaughter, and not onely giueſt licence, without puniſhment to deſtroy, not a citizen, but a magiſtrate, not a magiſtrate, but a king, but dooſt alſo moſt impudently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the déed, and teacheſt this to be the readieſt and ſpéedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way to heauen, with poiſon, ſword, fraude and treaſon to kill Kings, that are the maieſtie of mankinde, the true patterne of Celeſtiall power, and the liuelie Images of the King of Kings. And this is it, I thinke, <hi>Quod vix credat quiſquam cum narrabitur,</hi> That none will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue it, though it ſhall bée tolde them, becauſe the like was neuer heard amongeſt the Turkes. And the Tartarians,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14615:7"/>and barbarous nations when they come to heare it, wil for the ſtraungenes thereof, preſently ſhake and tremble. Is not this then great, cruell and execrable, great truelye it ſhould be, if yet greater did not follow after. Why doeſt thou quake Sixtus, can there be ſaide any thing more hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſer: I truly, we are fallen in thoſe daies, in the which the aboundance of wickedneſſe, maketh vs deſtitute of wordes, and in the which it is ſcarſe counted treſpas, which in times paſt hat béene moſt iuſtly executed as hie treaſon. So it is I ſay that the deſtinies of our age haue brought forth a villanous déede, not the like redde or hearde before. No time euer hath ſéene a king ſlaine by like treaſon, yet in the murther is ſomething that will rather frette thee, then make thée to maruaile. Why ſhould not the caſuall hande of this inraged murtherer accompliſh the like, that the premeditated and forecaſt counſel of the traitour hath performed? There haue béene ſome whom the wild boare hath ſlaine, ſome whom the ſtagge bring intangled in the nettes, ſome died by the vnſkilfull cutting of a vaine, ſome with the ſtroke of a horſe héele, and finally if we looke nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly vnto it, we ſhall finde almoſt ſo many kindes and ſundry deaths of kinges, as there haue béene princes. And therfore, I tremble not ſo much at the ſtrangenes of this as at the example thereof. I will not ſay, that thou the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of kinges in Chriſt, (for ſo thou loueſt to be tearmed) haſt béene grieued, mourned, wept, and called vpon God, the ſtrong reuenger of all iniquity, for this moſte heauy chaunce, and miſfortune of thy firſt begotten ſonne, but (ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide all piety and naturall affection) to haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken voluntarily and without compulſion the defence of the murtherer, maintayned with thy authority, argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and lawes, the nocent innocency, of this accurſed cut-throate, and in remembrance of thy ſonne, to haue moſt cruelly inueighed againſt his dead body, and this it is, Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, which I cannot heare, reade, or remember, with a quiet and vntroubled minde. Good God, I ſée in one crime, two offences, two hainous murtherers, him firſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14615:8"/>who moſt treacheroſlic hath aſſaulted his naturall Prince, then him who reuengeth not the deſtroyer of his ſonne, but excuſeth him, and is not contented to excuſe him, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth him, and doth not onely defende him, but praiſeth him, yea by a moſt exquiſite and ſingular compariſon, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizeth him amongſt his Saintes of Heauen. Auoid, auoide therefore hence, all naturall affection, Sixtus hath baniſhed thés out of the Romaine Empire. As long as hée raigneth goe viſite the Tartarians and Muſkouites, and other more barbarous nations if there be any, here are none that will intertaine thée, no not receaue thée without thy perill. But O yée Frenchmen, it were not manful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, to leaue vnreuenged the death of your moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King, who will ſuffer them to triumphe with proude orations, ouer the treacherous murthering of your prince? Let mée bée nothing eſtéemed off, if I reuenge it not, and requite this vnto thee, Sixtus, giue eare onely vnto mee, and that our poſterity may know thee, and thy vile and bloudy excutioner, and al thoſe that were of this conſpiracy firſt hear in ſhort and true words the chaunce of this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Potentate, that by the greatnes of the murther, all our ſucceſſion may iudge him guiltie hereof, that did defend it.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtoriographers haue written diuers cauſes of the originall of the ciuill wars, in the time of Charles the ninth, according as they were ledde with loue, and hate which they did beare vnto the Potentates, and Nobility of Fraunce, yet it is knowen to euery man, that after the departure of Henrie the thirde into Polonia, the houſe of Guiſe chiefely the two brethren Frauncis and Charles, Cardinalls, through a deſire of raigning, haue corrupted firſt their owne, and then all the counſell of the Realme. For Empires firſt of all muſt be troubled, and ſhaken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can bée ouerthrowne and ſubuerted. And from thence all theſe ciuill warres haue taken their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. At that preſent the Kinges houſe, was yet mighty and ſtrong, with diuers brethren and kinſemen: vnto whome the Crowne without contradicttion after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of the King belongeth. And vnleſſe they were all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14615:8"/>diſpatched, the Guiſes knew verie wel that their hope was but vaine. Amongſt the Kinges kindred, Lodowick prince of Condy was moſt feared, as one indewed with ſingular graces, and alone ſufficient to ſuſtaine all their attemptes, and to breake and bring to naught all their deſperate en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes. Who whether he now long ſince hath lefte this worlde, to the good or bad fortune of this Realme, through the popes authority, and ancient Romane religion, hauing followed as they ſay the better, (for at that time there was a great talke ouer all chriſtendome, of a reformation of all hereticall errors and opinions) I know not. But firſt they ſet vpon him accuſing him of hereſie, and corrupting of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which then was a difficult and hainous crime, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him firſt ſued in law, as an enemy of the apoſtolike Sea, preſently after perſecuted him with ſword and fire. He on the other ſide not diſprouided &amp; deſtitute of corage, frends and helpe, (the new religion now being ſpred in al citties of France, and euerie day the number of his increaſing, being likewiſe aided by the counſell of the chiefeſt and beſt of the Realme, who deteſted and hated the Guiſes great ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuſpected their power) did valiantly withſtand them. And here out is firſt come the vnhappy diſtinction of the names of Catholiks and proteſtants, and the deadly &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall diuiſion of this Realme, which I feare me, can neuer be agréede againe, vnleſſe by a long peace, and great loue, all cauſes of ambition, hee remoued and quite taken away: broils now being raiſed euery wher, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might haue béen eaſely repreſſed, vnles the fatal deſtinies of France had letted it, the Guiſes proclaime open war ayainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince of Conde and al heretikes, and eaſely perſwaded thervnto the king himſelfe, and his mother, a very deſperat and an auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious woman. And now ſéeing that they could bring his M. to conſent vnto al whereunto the thought good themſelues, for the ſmall experience which he dad, cauſed preſently all thoſe whom they thought were aduerſaries vnto their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til dealings, partly through feare and accuſation of the like offence of hereſie, to voide the court, &amp; by al means ſought
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14615:9"/>to ſtirre vp the reſt to ciuill iarres with a hope of ſpoile and ſuch like nouelties. Call moreouer Philip King of Spaine, and thy predeceſſor Sixtus, vnto their ayde. Promiſe vnto the king then occupied in the Lowe Countries, that France ſhould nothing hinder or moleſt him: and vnto the Biſhop of Rome an euerlaſting warre againſt the enemies of the holy Sea. For they perſwaded vnto themſelues that their intent could neuer, or hardly at the leaſt be brought to paſſe, as long as the common wealth flouriſhed with peace and quietneſſe, but it being once troubled and with ſeditions, diſquieted, ſhould make it eaſie, and this their thought was not amiſſe. For the Princes of the Royall bloud being all diſpatched, the ſtrongeſt and mightieſt of whom, was now aſſaulted with open warre, they hoped that the reſt ſhould eyther die in warre or for the affinitie which they had with the Prince of Conde in hope of the Crowne, would ſoone depart from the Court, and finally that then, Charles and his brethren but children, might be without labour conuayed away and murthered. And to that effect they began warre, and with theſe torches haue kindled firſt the fire of ciuill diſcorde in France: but the laſt deſtinies and extreme calamities of the Realme were not yet come, for as in our bodies a dangerous diſeaſe is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times long felt before, and with diuers paines and grieues the forces thereof are aſſaulted and wearied before they are broken and ouercome: euen ſo the like befalleth with Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires and kingdomes. But both the brethren departed firſt out of this world before they could accompliſh and make an end of their long practiſed enterpriſes. Francis died at the ſiedge of Orleans, at the thréeſcore and thrée yeares of his age, hauing left behind him thrée ſonnes, Henry Duke of Guiſe, Charles Duke de Mayne, and Lodouick a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall not yet come out of their childhoods. But in whom as there appeared ſparkes of domeſticall proweſſe, ſo in them ſéemed to be no feare of vice. Vnto whom he left not onely good ſtore of treaſure, and great reuenewes, but alſo a hope of a large Empire, his damnable practiſes, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14615:9"/>ſparkles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> warre. But in the meane while the king &amp; his brethren grew in age, before the Lions whelpes were capable of their fathers ferocitie, and ſo France turning her former mind, began to worſhip, honor, &amp; obay her Princes, now come to full age and full of courage &amp; magnanimitie, whom ſhe neuer before had ſéene but children. But chiefly reſpected Henry, whom comlines of body, perfect age, &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure in armes commended &amp; aduanced to the gouernment of outlandiſh Nations. And thus by little and litle their vaine ambition hath béene repreſſed, but in tract of time other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of euill were preſented. Charles dieth, whether by deſtime or poyſon it is vncertaine. And I haue no leaſure at large to diſcourſe vpon this point, &amp; to rehearſe from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning this tragidie: but yet this is moſt true, a litle before his departure out of this worlde, ſéeing his eſtate greatly weakned by the tediouſnes of war &amp; cruel murthers &amp; maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres euery day co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vpon his ſubiects, &amp; the treaſure of this Reamle conſumed &amp; ſpent, Italy &amp; Spain laughing at it, inuaighed with ſharpe &amp; threatning words againſt the authors hereof, and this was peraduenture the occaſion of his vntimely death. Henry the third ſuccéeded him, whom whether Polonia hath ſuffred with greater griefe to depart from thence, or France receiued him with more ioy it is doubtfull. He warned by his brothers example, as ſoone as he had ſet &amp; eſtabliſhed the affaires of his realme in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, gaue his mind wholly to the ſtudie of peace, knowing very well that riuill broyles are alwaies good for them that affect crownes and kingdoms, but naught to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raigne &amp; weare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. From hence is come the firſt originall of this miſchief, for thou &amp; thine Sixtus would neuer commend the kings moſt wholſom counſell, thy drifts tending to nothing els but by ſword &amp; fire to confirme thine own ſauegard, litle regarding by what law or with what condition one rained ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe periſhed together with their crowns whom thou didſt hate &amp; couldſt not abide. And ſo by litle &amp; litle the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſo many victories, and ſo many bloud-ſheds, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for the Sea of Romes ſake, grew ſtale, &amp; preſently
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14615:10"/>after enuie began to ſwel in the peoples minds daſly corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſeditious fermons of Friars, not delaying only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt godly vow of their Prince, but infecting it. And ſo it was eaſie to make an entrie for miſchiefe to follow. The Duke of Guiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time with his two brethren in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in age power and fauor by the Catholikes, as their father was before, &amp; at the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſundrie wayes vnto them, and hauing proſpered reaſonably vnder Henry being not yet come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crowne, ſaluted courteouſly euery one that met the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimpleſt amongſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, ſpake to them, &amp; left nothing vndoone to ſteale away the hearts of the commontie, all true ſignes &amp; tokens of an ambitious mind practiſing &amp; attempting ſome nouelties. Spread abroad falſe reports, to rayſe priuie grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; diſpleaſures amongſt the Nobilitie: and finally Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis the kings youngeſt brother being now departed out of this life either by ſicknes or fraud, ietted to &amp; fro through all cities beraied yet with the bloud of thoſe of the reformed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, fearing for their maſſacres a iuſt reuenge. Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon miſerie, &amp; vnleſſe there ſhould be looked vnto in time, affirmed that after the death of the king (which too true they ſayde ſhould be ere long) they all ſhould become ſubiects againe of an Heretike, &amp; endure all bondage, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, &amp; flauery whatſoeuer. But that they would diſplay their power againſt it, &amp; the promiſed and ready ſuccor of Spaine &amp; Italy, to defend &amp; protect by it their liberties, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike religion: theſe things are knowen vnto euery man, &amp; the king himſelf hath bin aduertiſed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by diuers ſpyes ſince the yeare 77. &amp; yet for lacke of puniſhment, as it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeene, grew maruellous ſtrong. Let therefore the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie iudge whether this is come to paſſe through too great a clemency, or by ſome fatall negligence of all French men.</p>
            <p>In the yeere 1585. <hi>Ianus</hi> temple being ſhut vp in France, &amp; a happy peace flouriſhing in all the realme, no external or domeſticall enemy once knowne, the Duke of Guiſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the houſe of Lorraine hauing conſpired together, take the weapons in haude, the only cauſe therof was a crowne,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14615:10"/>their cloake and probable occaſion, pietie &amp; religion, a care for the realme, now ill gouerned, a pitte to ſee the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with exactions pould and oppreſſed, and an intent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all things in good order. They hauing put this vizard vpon their rebellion, by their firſt writinges publiſhed in theyr names, complayned of the publicke calamities, of the weakeneſſe of the kings friendes, of the Realmes trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure waſted and ſpent, notwithſtanding the dayly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of tallages and tributes, and that the people were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnable longer to endure this beauie burthen. Beſides nothing. Something by the way as concerning religion and Heretikes. For vndoubtly they would not that ſo many ennemies ſhould be rayſed vp at once, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the king had drawen hatred and enuie enough vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his head by the gouernement of his realine, and that therefore they had ſufficient matter and occaſion of warre. It is moſt euident truly through the priuate grudge which they did beare vnto their king &amp; the Duke Eſpernon, that ſome ſmall and caſuall triſles of anger haue beene the firſt cauſe of theſe laſt troubles. In reuenge whereof ſo many dead bodyes, ſo many murthers, and finally the death of the king himſelfe, and the ruine of the whole Realine, haue all ſcarce ſuffiſed. But warned by a Spaniard who milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed the order of making the accounts of the Realine, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by thée Sixtus, that looked for no benefite to fall vnto thy ſhare by this warres, but by the ouerthrowe of the Heretikes, they chaunge their Enſignos, and proclayme open warre againſt thoſe of the reformed Religion.</p>
            <p>Héereuppon preſently the Pope ſent his thunderboltes, whereby he excluded the king of Nauarre (at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ruling in Fraunce) and the Prince of Cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard; innocent, and thinking nothing ſuch, from his Apoſtolicke bleſſing: but hereby may eaſely appeare, that God and none of the Apoſtles were preſent at the raſh iudgement of the cauſe. They nowe hauing turned their long, ſpake nothing more of the king, or his gouernement but only in his ſingular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation. Extolled the prime of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14615:11"/>his age, admoniſhed him of his former valour and proweſſe, and with exquiſite wordes ſhewed that the memorie of ſo many victories, wherewith he had ſo oſtentimes repreſſed &amp; abated the courage of the Heretiks, was yet recont &amp; freſh. That his time of reſt was not yet come, and that vnto ſuch a valiaunt and ſtrong Prince the victory of the battaile, and the ſlaughter of a whole nation belonged. Moreouer, they laide before his eies his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and want of children, and their miſeries wherin they were like to fall, if after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of ſuch a moſt Chriſtian king (with diſſembling wiſe they ſaide that they greatly ſeared) they ſhould be forced to ſubmitt themſelves vnder the yoke and bondage of an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke. Finally deſired his Maieſty, that it woulde pleaſe him, to appoint Charles of Borbon Cardinal, being weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with age and ſicke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> haſte vnto the Crown reiecting Nauarre: And breaking the alliance and treaty of peace, with the hereticks, ſhould take armes againſt them: which if he liked &amp; would perform, they neuer would refuſe any due obedience vnto him their lawful prince. Showed beſides that they had their ſwordes ready, and ſufficient wealth and aide, wherewith they might not onely reuenge themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppon the Heretickes, but alſo vpon their fauourers. The duke of Guiſe hauing ſpoken thus, not farrying if the King would further determine hereupon, hauing gathered forced for to aſſault thoſe of the reformed religion, made them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede to march agaynſt the King himſelfe, diſpoſſeſſed him partly by force and partly by pollicy, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch Citties as hée could, where the name of Luther or Caluin had neuer béen hearde, robbed their treaſure, impoſed new tributes vpon them, and finally where no ennemy was, exerciſed all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtſhty and eruchreſſe. The king in the meane time deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of courage and good counſel rather then of force, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted himſelfe, for his corupted friends told him wonders of the Ginſes power and army, and feared him that &amp; the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes ſhould but once heare the name of Hereticks, they would preſently all retire, and goe backe from him. That he ſhould linger therefore a while, vntill he had hearde the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14615:11"/>counſell of his néereſt friendes, who with all ſpéede if néede required would ſoone prouide all neceſſaries for the warre: and ouercom by the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of his mother, who alwaies had fauoured the contrarie ſide, and fraighted by the Ieſuites vaine ſuperſtitions was not brought but drawen therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. And ſo the articles of peace were agreed vpon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded betweene him and the duke of Guyſe, and warre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt thoſe of the reformed religion, vnto whom by generall proclamation was commanded to departe at the appointed tyme out of the realme, otherwiſe to ſtand to the aduenture and hazard of their liues.</p>
            <p>About the end of the ſame yeare great forces were ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp and enrolled, the duke de Maine was ordained chiefe ouer them, and being ſent into Guyan or Aquitane, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned next yeare againe wyth little good ſucceſſe, recalled, as they ſay, by his brother, who impatient of all delayes was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alike with enuy, anger, and ambition, cryed, that the ennemie was not for to be ſought for, that hee was at hand, and ſtoode before the doore, that the head of a Prince onely gréeued him, and hindred his enterpriſes, and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he onely was to be aſſaulted, emitting and leauing the other. And ſo riſeth againe againſt the king, being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in other warres: and that hee coulde not obtaine by his firſt rebellion, by this he forceth it. Complaineth, that his brother was forſaken in Aquitane, fruſtrated, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of men, money, and munition: as alſo that hee was not ſent ſooner againſt the enemie, before all the treaſure of the realme was ſpent for to lacke nothing. That theſe were ſure arguments, that the Catholikes were betrayed, that his Maieſties mind was corrupted by ill counſell: and thoſe whome he ſhould loue and embrace, that hee hated and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed them, and that therefore it could not be but hee had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the Heretickes. And finally, if hee reiected and diſherited not the king of Nauarre, and the Prince of Condy, and openly would appoint and declare a ſucceſſor, that there was nothing remayning, that all good and godly catholickes ſhould any longer commit their liues and ſafety
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14615:12"/>vnto the protection of a diſſembling Prince, who did all things wyth delay, and proclaimed warre wyth his tongue agaynſt them, and called for peace wyth his hearte. This was ſpread abroade, Souldiours are taken vppe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne a newe contracte of Peace was to bée made for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréement. The King at one tyme cumbred wyth two e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, thought it neceſſarie, that wyth one of them an appoynment was to be concluded, gaue care againe vnto his mothers counſell: and againe, by her meanes agréede wyth the Guyſe. Hée demeth him little, deliuereth vnto him the demaunded Cities, and commaundeth newe forces to be taken vppe, to inuade Aquitane the dwelling place of thoſe of the refournied Religion, and publiſheth agayne newe and cruell Ordinances and Statutes againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Guyſe nowe hauing obtayned his purpoſe, and thinking that he was crept farre enough in the peoples fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, to vndertake and enterpriſe whatſoeuer pleaſed him: and that the Prince was brought into ſufficient hatred, that all thinges were ſette in a hurlie burlie, that the heartes of the Communaltie were diſmayed, and that now but little hindered hym to come vnto his pretence, watched for a fitte opportunitie to bring to paſſe his long deuiſed practiſes, when Fortime almoſt daſhed and threwe hym downe vnawares. For reporte was ſpread, that a great armie of high Germanes was come already into the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of the Realme, to the ayde and aſſiſtance of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion. And moreouer, how the king of Nauarre hauing repulſed and driuen backe nine armies in the ſpare of two yearus, and ouerthrowne the Duke of Ioicuſe, made haſte for to goe méete the Germanes wyth his chrefeſt and choſen forces. Which reporte made the Duke, his alies, and conſpirators not a little amazed, fearing that the king now better aduiſed, and hauyng gotten a fitte opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to reuenge hymſelfe vppon their pride and arrogancie, might turne both the armies vppon them, vnſufficient and altogether vnable to reſiſt and wythſtand ſo great a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as alſo that they might be diſcomfited before, ere euer
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14615:12"/>they ſhoulde perceyue it. And their ſeare was not vaine altogether. For at the ſame tyme the King of Nauarre had ſent his Ambaſſadours vnto his Maieſtie, requeſting hym to vſe his, and the Germaine forces againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ennemie of the Realme. But héere it manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that the King was neuer more betrayed then at that preſent. Here ſure tokens are to be ſéene of his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and diſloyall counſell, which, if hée had vſed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the tyme, ſhoulde haue wythout any daunger re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered altogether his former libertie, reſtored his realme to her former grace, and eſtabliſhed an euerlaſting peace amongeſt his Subiectes. But God had otherwiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted it.</p>
            <p>The Duke of Guyſe at this tyme was forced to reſt and pawſe a whyle, but ſoone after incouraged agayne, by the counſell of his eſpeciall friendes, whom hée had alwayes about the kings perſon, and who were priuie vnto all hys ſecretes, ſetting aſide his fathers practiſes, had recourſe vnto his mothers pollicies. Hée writeth Letters vnto his Maieſtie, and wyth an humble ſtyle, indeuoureth to prooue his mind to haue bin gentle and tractable alwayes, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer repugnant vnto any contract of peace. Further prayeth him to impute rather all things paſt vnto the deſtinies, then vnto the malice of men, proteſting alſo, that he, and his, were alwayes minded to honour, ayde, and aſſiſte their Prince, whoſe death they feared therefore the more, becauſe his ſucceſſor was vnknowne, and like to be farre inferiour vnto him, and if they were reſolued of one doubt, that his Maieſty néeded not to doubt, but that all things then ſhould proſper and ſuccéed according vnto his owne wiſhing. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth him alſo a ſtrong aide againſt the inuading and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching Germans, &amp; with many words declareth, that the ancient enimies of the Realme were to be driuen out, who héeing once put to flight, they were like to enioy an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and a ioyfull peace. This is eaſely perſwaded vnto the king, his greateſt friendes about him, and eſpecially his mother ſtopping vp the way alwayes vnto good counſell.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14615:13"/>
            <p>And by theſe means the King of Nauarre his aduice moſt profitable vnto the Realme, being reiected and neglected, an entrie was made againe vnto all deceit and diſloyalty. The king aſſembleth a great armie together, and with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence doth incourage it, ſendeth the Duke of Guyſe before to ſtop the paſſage vnto the Germanes, and if he coulde not bring them to a battel, ſhould at the leaſt weary them with continuall I kirmiſhes and inuaſions. The king remained in the meane time about the riuer of Loyre. The German ſorces marched forward, and were come into the inwarde parts of the Realme wythout any reſiſtance, to the great feare and terrour of all the country. When the ſame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which not long before had almoſt ouerthrowen the Guyſe, preſenteth vnto him a farre brauer occaſion lucke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to procéede in his enterpriſe. For the ennemy béeyng brought by ſome croſſe lucke betwéene the Loyre and the Seine, and wearied wyth a long winter, continuall flouds and raines, want and diſtreſſe of al neceſſaries, were forced for their better ſafetie without delay to go ouer the riuer to ioyne themſelues wyth the king of Nauarre his forces. But the Duke of Guyſe preuented and ſurpriſed them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a ſodaine in the night, made a great ſlaughter amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them, and killed about twelue hundred of them, taketh many, and putteth the reſt to flight: and if Monſieur Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillion had not béene there at that preſent, all this great army ſhoulde haue béene ſcattered and ouerthrowen in one night: yet not wythſtanding the weake remnaunt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forward. And the King iealous of the victorie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth one parte of his forces vnto Eſpernon to purſue the ennemy, and hymſelfe followed not farre behinde. But hauing vnderſtoode the Germanes ſhamefull yéelding, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth againe to Paris.</p>
            <p>All ſtormes of feare now ouerblowne and paſt, the duke of Guyſe imboldened wyth this vnlooked for and good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, thought good not to ſéeke herehy ſo much praiſe, as thereby to procure all hatred and enuy vnto his Maieſtie. To that effect ſecret reportes were ſpread abroad, whereby
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14615:13"/>this new conquering Captaine was exalted and lifted vppe vnto the ſkie. The Germaine ſpotles, to wit their horſes, weapons, and all other array were ledde and carried in triumphe through the Citties. And when the people were flocked together in great troups, to ſée this new ſight, ther were alwaies certaine declarors and tellers of the battaile among them: The number of the dead perſons and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, was augmented, the manner of the fight was made very difficult, bloudy, and dangerous for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conquerors: and moſt of this was falſ, for it is wel knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> companies of Collonel Donon now heauy with wine and ſléepe, were ſurpriſed and oppreſſed, where they had no place to fight, or to eſcape. And that not one of the duke of Guyſes ſouldiers were found wanting. Beſides after the great ouerthrowe of ſo mighty an army, that ſuch ſmall remnants haue béen able to ouercome ſo many diſtreſſes, and come in ſafety to their iournies end: that it came not by any fault that might haue béene in the duke of Guiſe, but by the kings and the duke Eſpernons negligence and ſmall care, vnto whom he had left the chaſe of the weake remnand of pages and ſculli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons onely, hauing atchieued himſelfe all the difficulties of the warre, and either ſlaine or taten the choſen and valli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Captaines and ſouldiers therof, And notwithſtanding al this, that by their meanes they were al ſafely arriued to the king of Nauarre, to depriue the victorie of her due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and prayſe, and to hinder therewith the more the good commodities that might haue enſued herby vnto the whole realm. That they at the firſt followed then for very ſhame, but ſo ſlackely, that they that were already vanquiſhed, might eaſely eſcape without running. And now when they ſawe, that the hurt, wearie, and ſicke men could not fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way or eſcape, who ſhould haue al béene put to the ſword, or at the leaſt impriſoned, by the lawes of armes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Realme, to haue giuen and graunted vnto them (for a counterfaite yeelding and ſubmiſſion onely) their lifes, horſes, and furniture, therewith to inuade the Realme againe, and moreouer vnto ſome of them all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14615:14"/>their goods. By theſe deuiſes, hatered and enuy, being procured and prouoked: the ill aduiſed Prince, but to late, acknowledging his errour, in vaine began to wiſhe for this moſt fitte and neglected opportunity of reuengement, yet being come to Paris, ſpendeth the reſt of the winter in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring and renewing of his forces, publiſhing an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition againſt thoſe of the reformed religion, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe prepared the next Sommer following, either by theſe meanes to drawe againe vnto him the heartes of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty altogether affectionated vnder the coullour of religion vnto the Guyſe, or that hée had determined to doe it, importunated thereunto by the Ieſuites continuall outcries, aſſuring him daily of certaine argumentes of Gods wrath againſt the Heretikes, and in briefe a happye end and iſſue of all his warres againſt them.</p>
            <p>In the year eightie eight, which was feared ſhould haue béene fatall vnto all the Worlde, the Guiſe taketh new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and counſaile, howe to come to a happie end of his long continued hope, and to enioy the fruites thereof. Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that ſo oftentimes ciuill warres haue béene moued in daine againſt the king of Nauarre, whereof the iſſue was doubtfull, the profite vncertaine, or to late at the leaſte. That his Maieſty could not bee deceiued, but coulde be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one of two ennemies once being diſpatched, that with leſſe labour the other was to be ouerthrown and vanquiſhed. That he had al thinges ready to ſuppliant the firſt, and then afterwarde would fall vppon him who was yet remayning. That it was to bee haſtened, and not to bee ſlepte vppon. Beginneth therefore now no leſſe to hate and enuy the King, then before he had done the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes. That Fortune had offered him this good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, which if hee ſhoulde let it ſlippe by, hee might wiſhe afterward for it, when it was paſt recouery. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer (the Germaines nowe repulſed) that nothing was remaining that might cauſe him to feare. That al hope of out landiſhe aide and aſſiſtance was cut off vnto the King of Nauarre, by whoſe faulte all Germany and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14615:14"/>England did crie out, that ſo great an army, ſo many Nobles, and ſuch number of valiaunt Captaines and ſouldiers were diſcomfited and ſlaine. And that the king himſelfe was ſore wearied and broken with long during warres, and although Conquerour of many battailes, yet had loſt notwithſtanding all the chiefeſt of his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and thoſe that were eſcaped, either for want, and néede, or for a deſire of quietneſſe, wiſhed onely for peace. And that with them therefore hee ſhoulde haue but litle to doe: hereupon thinking moſt expedient not to make any further delayes, furiouſly taketh now the thirde time the weapons in hand: meſſage is brought vnto his M. and reports euery where ſpred abroad, not as before, that Citties are ſurpriſed, that the people riſe in armes, that muſters are taken, and ſuch like ſignes of miſchiefe yet far off, and to be preuented diuers waies, but that the Duke commueth in perſon himſelfe. And no ſooner was it ſpoken, but he was ſéene in déede, arriueth in Paris very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely (where the king was at that time) where hee had laid long before ready and truſty ambuſhes, partly for the mutinous mindes of that common people, as alſo for the great number of conſpirators in that Citty: as it is moſt certaine that no where kinges and princes can be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier oppreſſed then in their imperiall Citties. But the firſt night of his arriuall he was quiet, wearied (God hauing ſo diſpoſed it, for the Prince his ſafegard yet altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided) that all thinges were not yet currant and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. But next day morning ſoundeth alarme, putteth the kings garriſons to the ſword, and marcheth directly to the Louure his Maieſties pallace, with the mutinous &amp; bloudy people to beſiege their ſworne Prince. The king amaſed at this ſudain accident and vpror, vnto whoſe honor it ſtood not to fly away, not to his ſafety to expect his enemy w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage in no indifferent place, yet w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the lord chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſouldiers, and with his gard of Switzers reſiſteth their aſſalts for a day or twaine. But ſéeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to arm themſelues againſt him, &amp; al things to go backward w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14615:15"/>and no hope of any helpe or ſuccour, eſcaped ſafely among the inraged clamours of the deſperate multitude, crying nothing but ſworde and fire, and came to Lions. The wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded and affectionated ſubiects vnto their King, coulde not brooke and beare ſuch an outragious iniury. Their hearts turned therfore vppon a ſuddaine, &amp; the caſe now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, doe pitty their Prince. The pillers of the Realme, the nobility, the commons, and the better and ſounder part of the cleargie came in poſte vnto his Maieſty. They exclaime all againſt the houſe of Lorraines great preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſaid that puniſhment was to be done which ſhould equal, or rather excéede the greatneſſe of the offence. They pronuſe vnto the king all aide and furtherance, if it woulde onely pleaſe him (giuing ouer all other, yea rather the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes themſelues who neuer dared the like) to ouergoe this gréefe. The king ſubiect vnto his deſtiny, ſéemeth to bee tourhed with this readineſſe of his affectionated ſubiectes, but yet is nothing moued with it. But thanketh euery one very ſoberly, as if he had had no néede at all, aunſwereth quietly vnto them, that hée wanted neither courage nor force to reuenge his priuate iniuries, and that it was not néedefull to ſuſtaine two ciuill wars in one realme, where one ſufficed, &amp; was rather too much. And herwith ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al home againe, intending againe reconciliation. If the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity wil beleue one telling the truth, let it without doubting beléeue this with mée, that nothing more touched and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the hearts of Frenchmen, then to ſee their Kings great patiency, not deſpiſing, but ſcarce approuing the moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mindes of his ſubiects, in the reuengement of the publike and common ſhame and diſhonor. Let the poſterity alſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon my word, holdly ſay that Ouéene Katherine his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was the only cauſe of his deadly ſound and vnſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vnto whoſe faithfull helpe and aide, the Guyſe tooke his refuge, as ſoone as hée perceaued that his matters wold not forge, and that the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people were altered for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> done vnto the king, and that the Nobility, and the chieſeſt of his beganne to bée diſcomforted, diſcouraged,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14615:15"/>and drawe backe from him. Now this third time Henry giueth place vnto his mothers aduice, and hearkeneth vnto her counſell: now this third time an agréement is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with great ioy of all the conſpirators, who thought it to be no ſmal fauor thus eaſily to haue eſcaped deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for their mutinie and rebellion. But the wiſe yet feared in generall that this wound could not be cloſed vp and healed without a foule ſearre remayning, or that hee who had once preſumed to beate his Prince out of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Citie, ſhould not want audacitie to attempt ſome further matter. All things now pacified, a Parleament is proclaimed and publiſhed, generally to determine vpon the common affaires of the lande, vpon an agréement of the adminiſtration of the Realme, for aſſurance of ſucceſſion of the Crowne: and finally that theſe ſmall tinnults &amp; iarres (for ſo the conſpirators of the kings ouerthrow and ſworne his bane termed it onely,) might haue an end and reaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Catholikes, that a mortall warre ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and concluded againſt the Heretikes. But the king and the Guiſe, had farre different and contrarie meanings: the Prince his intent was, now hauing recouered againe his authoritie, to bridle the common enemie of France con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by full Parleament. But how difficult and hards this was to doe, and how full of trouble and daunger, the euent and iſſue thereof hath taught it vnto vs. The Guiſe on the otherſide to exclude the king of all gouernement by the authoritie of the whole eſtate, that vnto him onely (Nauarre and the reſt of the bloud royall ſupplanted) the adminiſtration of the whole Realme might be committed. And ſo farre he had almoſt brought it, none being come to this generall Counſell, but thoſe that were of the conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie.</p>
            <p>And ſo the Parleament was kept at Bloys, where the king ſhewed at large in the face of the full aſſembly, his great affection towards the Catholikes, his benefits ſundry times moſt largely beſtowed vpon them, how many victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries be had gotten vpon the Heretikes, how oftentimes he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14615:16"/>had altogether diſcomfited and put them to flight, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of them he had ſent to Hell, being in manner but a childe: and now a man that he had no leſſe ſtomacke &amp; courage then he had in his yonger age. And that he neuer was minded to ſuffer in his realm any religion, contrary to the ſeruice of God. But that he had bene forced through the peoples great miſerie &amp; want, wearied, and diſcoraged with ſo many ciuill warres to diſſemble his deſire and meaning. And to delay all thinges till a fitter time and opportunitie, which could not haue béene vrged at that inſtant without great danger. But that he had alſo learned by ſundrie try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alles, and long experience, that by peace and generall qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, the corrupted minds of the inconſtant people were with leſſe labour drawne vnto godlineſſe, then when by the ſound of warre once noyſed abroade, and by the brightnes of ſwordes and armours once ſéene and perceiued great li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to al licentiouſnes, was giuen to mutinous &amp; ſeditious heads: that the church was not to be reformed and purged by villanies, wherewith all wars were for the moſt parte infected, but chiefly the domeſtical &amp; ciuil broiles: But that it was to be done, by godly maners, good examples, by the preaching of the worde of God, by humilitie, and feruent prayers. That this hath béene his only mind, euen when the Guyſe in the yere 1585. took firſt the weapons in hand, troubled the people &amp; common peace, wherunto he was not yet altogither repugnant: but forced for the general welfare of his ſubiects, that he armed himſelf ful ſore againſt his wil, &amp; that nothing now was remaining which was not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med &amp; waſted by wars. He reckoned them the armies ſince the time of 3. yéers, and how much money there was ſpent in: and that it gréeued him very much, that ſo many valiant ſoldiers were deſtroyed, ſo great a treſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed in waſte, wherwith a great kingdome might haue bene ioined to his. But thus far more, that he had in the meane time receyued more harme and dammage by his friends, then euer hée had done by his enemies, and that the iſſues of his wars &amp; victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries had bin rather hindered and ſtopped by the ambition of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14615:16"/>ſome, then by the forces and power of the enemie preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. That he was notwithſtanding fully determined not to lay down the weapons, before he had ouerthrowen &amp; quite rooted out all the rebelles, although they all ſhould ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, &amp; ſhould be feared that it might turne to the vtter ruine &amp; deſtruction of the whole realm: that at the leaſt this cloake and coullour being taken away, he might be able to hold &amp; kéepe euery man from hence forward in their duetie &amp; obedience. That therefore they ſhould determine by what meanes, what money, &amp; ſouldiers this might be done moſt commodiouſly. That they were called to that intent. As touching the other affaires of the realme, as the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Clergie, of the treaſure, eaſie ſubſidies, tributes, and fallages, ſetteth downe ordinances and cauſeth thereof writings to be made. The Commiſſioners &amp; aſſignes bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto the Kings doubtfull Oration with a merry and gnatonical countenance, &amp; with many flattering words ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing praiſed him in whoſe ouerthrow &amp; vndooing they were aſſembled and ſworne, demanded a certaine time to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine vpon it. And in the meane while y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this was a doing not without the great expectation of all men, <hi>ludos homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus dens facit,</hi> they féede the king onely with fancies.</p>
            <p>The Guiſe fearing that the Prince (prouoked with ſo many iniuries) would not ſuffer long theſe delaies, and that he would ſéeke, and finde meanes for reuenge: and ſéeing that all had bended their eyes vpon him, and expected for ſome greater thinges which ſhould farre excéede the firſt: that Naua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e without iuſtice and law vnheard and not to be heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reiected and condemned: that nothing was wanting but to diſpatch the Kings <hi>ſimul  ardet &amp; audet,</hi> both moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſires it, and dares it.</p>
            <p>He charged euery man being of the conſpirators to prouide, and prepare the reſt. This charge hee vndertooke himſelfe, this burden he layd vpon his owne ſhoulders: And thinking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now the time was come to make a happie end of his fathers before, but now his enterpriſes, calleth the chiefe of the conſpiracie, amongſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were Ledonick the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14615:17"/>Cardinall his brother and the Arch-biſhop of Lyons the chiefeſt. Vnto them and vnto ſome few other he declareth and ſheweth in what ſtate his matters ſtande, ſayth that al things are brought to ſome effect, that nothing is obſtant but the Prince only, beſides that he was driuen to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, that eyther hee or the king muſt periſh. That they therefore ſhould ſée, whether he were to be diſpatched, or vntill ſuch times impriſoned till all thinges were confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and eſtabliſhed for a new gouernement. And that there was no other meane or <hi>medium</hi> to be found. They cry all that this is not to be delayed, that fetters and priſon are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnprofitable, that no caue or denne how déepe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, were able to kéepe cloſe ſo great and mightie a poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, as long as he liued would alwayes thirſt after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, but as ſoone as he ſhould be diſpatched, that new deuiſes ſhould be practiſed, newe counſels taken, and that euery man would rather fall againe to their priuate, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſure commodities, then to attempt olde and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enterpriſes. But contrariwiſe if he were kept pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, it would ſéeme cruell and ſtrange vnto the common people, and altogether vntollerable. That they of late af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the kings flying away from Paris, had found and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by experience that pittie preuailed more then fauour. Finally that hereupon they néeded not long to beate their braines: but that hee was to be conuayed away and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched out of hande, Hereunto they all condeſcend. Now vpon the death of their Lord the ſeruantes determine, the annointed of the Lord and reuerented of ſo many Nations is bequeathed vnto their bloudie ſwordes. The day nowe appointed, and their deſperate wickedneſſe ſealed with an oth, they all depart. It was not néedefull to haue any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying hereof, for it was not vnknowen, but vnto them which were remooued into the vtmoſt partes of Europe, that this was the Guiſes pretence, and had béene long ſince. To what end tended elſe the arming of his rebellious bandes, ſo often againſt his Prince? But certaine it is that he was aduertiſed by the Duke de Mayne yet liuing of his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14615:17"/>brothers vngodly practiſes wyth theſe words: that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty ſhould take héede of a furious and deſperate mind. And one of the conſpirators (as it is moſt alwayes ſéene in ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like actions) moued in conſcience, diſcloſed vnto his Maieſty the whole conſpiracie, the day appointed, the tokens, the conſpirators themſelues: but in ſo ſhort a tyme, that he had ſcarce opportunitie to eſcape this imminont daunger. The king now deſtitute of al meanes of deliberation, and beaton wyth his owne rod, ouerthrowed not the conſpirators, but preuented them in one day.</p>
            <p>There was hope that this burning fire of ciuill broyles ſhould haue bin quenched, ſéeing that the flaming torches of theſe tumults were now extinguiſhed. And it pleaſed God, Sirtus, that France ſhould nowe enioie peace, but not thy Holineſſe. Hereupon the conſpirators, who were not the better, but the greater parte beganne to hang downe theyr heades, to ſéeke holes to hide themſelues, and through feare to runne to their holdes and places of defence. One parte gaue ouer their enterpriſe, and brake their faith giuen. But ſhortly after when they ſaw, that the Prince by ſome fatall and diſaſterous leuitie, vſed no further rigour againſt them, that he was ſatiſfied wyth the puniſhment of two only, that he had but impriſoned ſixe, and had ſent away the reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched: and that the ſiege of Orleans which hée had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne to batter but ſlackely, was rayſed by the comming of the Mayne. Then ſuddenly they beganne to runne as mad men, beganne to ſtrike alarme, to ſurpriſe Citties, to ſlaunder the name and credite of their Prince, wyth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe outragious ſpeaches: To diſanull and aboliſhe the Lawes, the Magiſtrates, and all that was royall in the Realme, all that was ſacred and auncient, and to induce newe, ſtrange, and intollerable ordinances. Finally, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wyth a ſenſleſſe fury, to exerciſe tyranny and crueltie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelues: inſomuch, that almoſt no Citie or towne hath eſcaped, their owne Citizens maſſacres, robberies, baniſhments, proſcriptions, and yet farre greater cruelties then the enemy himſelfe coulde haue imagined. And this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14615:18"/>through a iuſt iudgement of God, iuſtly taking vengeance, for ſo many murthers, ſheading of innocent blood, and innumerable villanies by them committed. And by theſe moanes, a more deſperate, and bloodie warre then euer was before, is nowe renewed. The Mayne who a little before had béene the bewrayer and accuſer of his brothers treaſon, is choſen chiefe of theſe inraged and deſperate companies. When uppon ſuddenly the whole Realme beginneth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell. And truly (freely I would haue it to be ſpoken) by the kings owne fault, who euer had reiected al good, wholſome, and profitable counſell, before he was driuen to theſe extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Parts gaue vnto the reſt an example of rebellion, as it was reaſon, ſhe being the firſt, inriched with ſundry gifts of kings, and the imperiall of the Realme. All the reſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, few onely excepted. And as they were before ſtriuing who ſhoulde be more affectionated vnto his prince, ſo nowe they contend who ſhal excéed in outragiouſnes againſt him. And to the end that nothing ſhould be wanting to the fulnes of their treacherie, they require and ſéeke for thy authoritie Sixtus, for the iudgements, of the diuines, for the conſent of the clergis, and al was preſently at their command. Urban, one of the Magiſtrates in Paris, demaunding in the full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of the Sorbonne, <hi>Whether the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men could be godly and honeſtly releaſed from their other made vnto the king.</hi> Anſwere was made, that they could. This anſwere is brought vnto the Magiſtrate, and with drawne ſwords is commaunded to approoue the ſame. The Senat flatly denieth ſuch a wicked acte to be lawfull &amp; worthy of the ancient loyaltie of France. And ſitting a little vpon it, the mutinous people brake ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gates of the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and ſelfe not vpon one or two of the Magiſtrates, but vpon them all, and caſt the whole bench in priſon, the onely maieſtie of the Realme. Preſently a newe Counſell is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, which approouing the anſwere of the vngodly diuines, diſchargeth the people of their othes: thruſt the king out of his kingdome. The Clergie commendeth this new counſel, and preſently hereupon the noyſe of the Popes thunderbolte
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14615:18"/>is heard, rowling from the high Capitoll, and threatening foorthwyth, as they ſayde, the ouerthrowe of all the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall mountaines of France.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1589. the king beeing at that inſtant at Blois, tydings was brought vnto his Maieſtie, that Paris, Roan, Lions, Tholouſe, and the cities of the Realme were all reuolted, and that not one was remaining which was not inſected with ſome notable treacherie. It was told vnto his maieſtie alſo how Briſac, Boidaulphin, and the lorde Chaſtre, whom he had ſuffred to goe home vntouched vpon their othes vpon the Guyſes death, had broken their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſo ſolemnely confirmed, &amp; were reuolted to the enimy. Moreouer, that the Spanyard, the Italian Princes, the Dukes of Loraine and Sauoy, together with the inraged &amp; furious people had ſworne the Guiſes reuengement. That he was not in ſafety in Bloys, whereſoeuer be turned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that all places were ſurpriſed, and vntruſtie. That at the one ſide the conſpirators did preſſe him, at the other ſide the king of Nauarre wyth a great power came to inuade the realme, being alreadie at Samure, and had taken all the cities thereabout.</p>
            <p>The king thus croſt with ſo many troubles and aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at once, penſiue what to do, and put aſide from al other hope, is forced to apply the vttermoſt remedy to an extreme fore &amp; diſeaſe, and that which he had neglected in the ful proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of his wealth, power, and gouernment, craueth now voluntarily, being almoſt diſpoſſeſſed of his crowne &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Calleth (not without gods appointment) to his aid the king of Nauarre his mortall enimy, but his moſt neceſſarie and profitable friend, if long before he had vſed him. He, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though greatly-iniured and offended, although ſo oftentimes at the Guyſes requeſt, by him aſſaulted with war: preſently vnlooked for, commeth to the king his brother, with a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen army, not only great in number, but alſo in valor, ſo that euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſouldier might haue ſupplied the roome of anie officer. A great change is nowe againe to be ſéene: for at the arriuall of this mightie prince and vnlooked for armie,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14615:19"/>the hearts of all the good, being herewith incouraged, and of the conſpirators terrified: de Maine himſelfe (to repreſſe and ſtay by his preſence the common report of the people, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining already againſt the intollerable inſolences of the ſouldiours, and féeling a dearth of all maner of victuals and neceſſaries, commonly the only cauſes of vproares and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in great cities) is conſtrained to returne again to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, with his mutinous companies which hee had brought from thence into the territories of Tours, to place them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where in garriſons. His departure was not vnlike a cowardly running away, the K. of Nauarre following him ſo neere vpon his héeles, that he put al the hindermoſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; all ſtraglers to the ſword. His maieſty in the meane time fortified with a power of Switzers, &amp; incoraged with ſome good ſucceſſe againſt the rebelles, commeth in perſon in his camp, and marcheth directly to Paris with al his forces, to puniſh them for their treacherie &amp; rebellion. Help commeth to him from all parts, his bands increaſe dayly in number, fame, and power. The ſtate of the realm thus ſuddenly cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (as the hearts of men are commonly inconſtant and wauering) the chiefe cities beginne to intreate vpon peace: the German and Italian Princes, to ſend ambaſſadors, to wiſh wel to his M. to promiſe him mony and men, and ſome of the firſt conſpirators alſo through diſpaire flie to his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. All thinges finally, fal contrary vnto the Guiſes exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, now out of all hope to looke any more, as long as the King liued, for any condition of agréement, or ſurety of life.</p>
            <p>The conſpirators all begin to tremble at this new and ſuddaine chaungement doubtfull what to doe, or to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take: yet the ring-leaders of the rebellion aſſemble togither in counſell, to determine vppon the extremitie of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. One among the reſt, whoſe name ſhall be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and ſpread abroade by his execution, declareth the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wherein they liue, what they haue in France leſſe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. That the minds of the nobilitie were mutable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, falling alwayes on fortunes ſide. That the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Cities coulde not bée kepte faithfull vnto them, vnleſſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14615:19"/>they were partakers of the like rebellion and treachery, &amp; if liberty were giuen vnto them, that ere long they woulde reuolte to the king again. That the cleargie was couetous and neuer did giue but little of their own vnto their kings, that therefore there was but ſmall hope that they woulde giue more vnto them that could and might but intreate for it. That this was their caſe at home: from abroad leſſe hope was to be looked for. That the Spaniard was olde, &amp; carefull for the quietneſſe of his owne family, vnto whome it was more ſurer, that France were troubled, then vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by any, but himſelfe. That the Italian Princes were circumſpect and wiſe, and thoſe of Germany couetous and miſers. That the Pope was ſubtill, crafty, and inconſtant, gréedy for his own gain, &amp; turning with euery blaſt of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. That therefore all his hope ſtoode in himſelfe, if they had any good ſucceſſe that they ſhould want nothing, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that they néeded not to looke for any help &amp; ſafety but in their héeles and flight. Finally that by the death of one King all their affaires might bée repaired, and that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was to be intended and labored, how &amp; by what meanes the Prince was to be diſpatched or murthered. That there was no other remedie for the redreſſe of their diſtreſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Hereunto they apply all their witte and induſtry, and there are not found wanting ſome, who offered themſelues to be miniſters of this villanous trechery. Many are ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prouoked thereunto by great promiſes, according as they had a quickneſſe of hand to performe ſuch an act, &amp; a deſperate audacitie of mind to dare vndertake it. Amongſt them al, Sixtus, is found Clement th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> welbeloued, a Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Iacobin, fit and ready for ſuch a trecherous enterpriſe, yer truſting not ſo much vppon his owne boldneſſe, wherin not withſtanding hée greatly did excell all his fellow-friars: then knowing that Friars, but chiefely thoſe of his order, had alwaies had a frée acces vnto his Maieſty, wher other verie ſeldome were admitted but at certaine howrs. This from his youth of hauing béene brought vp in the monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie very-poorely, hath giuen oftentimes notable tokens of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14615:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>his vngodly inclination and vilde diſpoſition (which many haue heard out of the Deanes owne mouth) and for his lewdneſſe, by their order of diſcipline hath béene often di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly puniſhed, yet nothing to his amendement, was moſt often taken in ſtews and whore houſes, oftentimes aſſaied to runne away. No godlineſſe, piety, or learning hee had, no not ſo much as the knowledge of the French letters, which any wayes might haue commended him. Which I think good to be ſpoken of this accurſed murtherer, that our poſterity may iudge, whether thy words are worthy of a ſacred mouth, that doth not make God only himſelfe priuy of manſlaughter, (pardon I craue O Iehoua) but farther doſt preſume to ſay, that he hath communicated vnto a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate bloudſhedder the giftes of his ſpirite, and ſuch moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the minde, which haue beene graunted only vnto his Prophetes and Apoſtles. This Friar nowe ſent out of Paris, goeth directly to the Campe, vppon this prouiſo notwithſtanding, that all thoſe that were ſuſpected to bee of the Kinges ſide, ſhould be kept faſt within the Cittie, wherevppon his life did ſtand altogether. Thoſe whom bee met firſt, ſolde them, that he brought letters and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings from certaine Pariſians who were greatly affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and known vnto the King, that they contained mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great importance. And that hee beſides had other things, to be diſcloſed vnto none but vnto his Maieſty: her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uppon was brought vnto the king with like facillity, as all the reſt of his order were before. Gréeteth the king but ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and yet ſcarſe ready, and at ſuch a time, as he was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to bee alone, deliuereth the letters, the which when his M. had peruſed, demanded him what newes he brought. The Friar falleth vpon his knées (the king at that preſent ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in a chaire, and inclining his eare to heare what hee would ſay) ſtabbed him with a knife which he had made &amp; poiſoned for that purpoſe. The prince hereuppon crieth out, the Lordes preſently come running into his chamber, after many wounds ſlay this curſed and moſt miſerable wretch Clemens, as alſo him that came with him, although the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14615:20"/>king did moſt earneſtly forbid it, for to learne by them, the order of the conſpiratis, the ſignes tokens, and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, who if they were knowen, as no double they ſhall be yet hereafter: I can not tell, Sixtus, whether<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou ſhalt bee able to ſhake from thy ſouldiers the ſuſpition of this bloudy crime, or at the leaſt to haue béene the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentor of this vngodly counſell. But the author of truth hath kept it to himſelfe till the time of thy puniſhment. Great heauineſſe and ſorrowe was ſeene in al the Campe, but greate ioye among the ennemy, whoſe reioyſing voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were hearde at that inſtant, demanding one of another whether the Friars knife was ſufficiently ſharpe or not. The King thus wounded was laid in his bed, wher he yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his ghoſt vnto God the next night following, hauing before made his will and ſet al things in good order.</p>
            <p>Here haue you hearde the ende of this mighty Prince, and here may you beholde as in a looking glaſſe, the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of a whole Realme. I ſee many thinges in it to bee lamented: Whereſoeuer I turne my ſelfe, I can perceaue nothing but a dreadfull horrour, a cruell, and blouddy ſpectacle, yet nothing more heauily doth preſent it ſelfe afore vs, then thine Oration, Sixtus, an ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus to the common griefe. Farre bee ſuch a ſhame from vs (lette it ſuffice vs, to haue loſt a good Prince, and that by our owne faulte and negligence) as to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the name of the dead to bée ſlandered and defamed, and the Monuments of ſo many worthy acts deſtroyed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I demand firſt of thée Sixtus, by what lawes that I ſhall contend with thée? With Chriſtian lawes? But what haſt thou to doe with Chriſt, whoſe birth and buriall thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>landereſt with a moſt deteſtable murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers compariſon? With the lawes of nature? but by what bandes of nature can bee vpholden the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of willfull murther? Howe then, with the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil lawes? The ſtatutes of Princes and the ciuill lawes haue enacted diuers and ſeuere puniſhmentes vnto thoſe that offended but by chaunce: but vnto thoſe that reuenged
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14615:21"/>their priuate quarrell by their own authoritie, fearfull tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. What puniſhments doe they alot then vnto thoſe who violat &amp; ouerthrow the welfare af a common wealth, truly almoſt incredible. But I ſee that I am conſtrained to ſéeke out new lawes to deale with thée, I am ready for it. Thou the autor of new offences, ſhalt bée my lawe and witneſſe, Europe the court, and the Heauens the Iudges, and vpon theſe equall conditions I will pleade againſt thée. Come then and hearken firſt vnto this, It ſéemeth verie ſtraunge vnto mee, and therefore make me ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquainted with it, that thou ſo oftentimes vſurpeſt the worde of <hi>Gods iudgement.</hi> Could not this ſuffice thee, to know God to bée the beſt of all goodneſſe? but to ſay that hée willed ſuch a deteſtable and wicked act. In déede wée ſée euerie where his wonderful iudgements: and we know that Princes the larger their gouernement hath béene, the greater accounts they haue to make. Beſides if kinges had committed any offence, that not onely themſelues did ſmart for it, but ſometimes all their ſubiects felt the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof. Both is to be ſéene in the holie Scriptures. I will not deny, but that this prince hath ſuffered deſerued puniſhment, if thou doeſt regard God onely, in whoſe eies all thinges are corrupt, naught, and crooked, nothing entire, or vndefiled,. But leaue the iudgement hereof vnto God, not vnto thy ſelfe, Sixtus. How knoweſt thou whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this is in ſtéede of a bleſſing and benefit, which thou thinkeſt to be a curſe, and a puniſhment. Did not Ioſias al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo die an vntimely death? doth not God moſt often cal them firſt vnto him whom he loueth: Are tirants not ſéene often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to raigne and liue longeſt? and good princes ſeldome come to great age? Superfluous, nay too curoius it were, Sixtus, to ſearch &amp; examin theſe things, &amp; more impious to iudge them. But let it be ſo, I grant this vnto thée. Shall therfore the excuſe and cloake of Gods iudgement, protect &amp; defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of a murtherer? the king of France for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences hath deſerued ſome heauy puniſhment at Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds doth it follow therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he is to he accounted godly, great,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14615:21"/>famous, happy, and worthy the title of an Emperor, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer of the common people the moſt abiect and vileſt, ſhall haue murthered his Prince? Then with thée that ſonne ſhall be accounted innocent, that is a reuenger of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers offence by his fathers death: and the indignation of thoſe children eſtéemed iuſt ſpilling the bloud of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes in Gods quarrell. What? is he worthy any longer to be reuerenced and honored with the title of a father, who liketh the example of naturall affection violated and quite extinguiſhed? Herewith thou art touched Sixtus, but wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore art thou ſo ſoone afeard, thou haſt no cauſe yet to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, theſe are but toyes and trifles, come but néere, for to heare that which ſhall not make thée pale, but altogether ſenſeleſſe. Let firſt the lawes of bloud and nature, which are the ſacred bandes of humaine ſocietie depart and goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, for as long as they are preſent I haue no reaſon to ſpeake any word at all. I grant againe that it is lawfull by thy lawes to kill parents condemned by iudgement, and an executioner not to be wanted in the citie, as long as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſonne is found preſent. Let thy iudge then pronounce ſentence and ſay, <hi>That lawfully the ſonne may kill the father,</hi> but let him adde vnto it at the leaſt, accuſed, noted, and condemned of a notorious offence, as an enemie vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, that by theſe meanes the priuate lawes of a familie may be diſanulled, by thoſe which concerne the publike vtilitie. But contrariwiſe if thou deſtroyeſt the publike commoditie by a publicke offence, away with thy lawes, for they cannot be exogated with the welfare of a common wealth. Let vs now ſée then: Here lyeth wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his bloud, not the father of a priuate familie, but hée of a great kingdome: not the griefe of one houſehold, but the heauineſſe and ſorrow of a whole realme moſt treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly procured. And yet doeſt thou commende this? and ſayeſt that he is murthered worthely? Well let it be ſo, ſo that he for whom we mourne be too worthy for to die af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a manner. But what was the offence in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge whereof, the diuine, the ciuill, the common, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14615:22"/>lawes did ceaſe and loyter? Thou ſayſt that he hath commanded Lodouick the Cardinall, the Guiſe his brother to be executed, whoſe conſecrated head was not to be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched but only by full authoritie from the Biſhop of Rome. Thou cruell beaſt doſt thou ſay that it is not lawfull for a King, ruling onely by Gods grace and authoritie to puniſh traytors againſt his Maieſtie, and conuicted ſo oftentimes to haue troubled the publike peace? and that it is permitted vnto a graceleſſe Friar to ſtabbe a Prince, for to haue iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed a Cardinall? What ſay ye to this O ye Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Europe, vpon whoſe neckes this cruell and bloudie Lyon treadeth. If he were to be puniſhed, it was not to be done after that order, witneſſes were to be produced, the offender was to be heard, iudges to be choſen &amp; no haſt was to be made vpon the execution of ſo great a Potentate. As if he wanted witneſſes, by whoſe ambition now 3. yeares together France hath béene diſquieted with ciuill warres: but his execution was to be delayed, to what end? To the troubling of good men, to the murthering of his Prince, &amp; to the ruine and ouerthrow of the whole realme, all which but a day before was preuented. But heare ſirha, by what law doſt thou exempt thy diſciples of common iuſtice more then any other? Forſooth that the lawes ſhould ſhew rigour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euery poore wretch for euery ſmall treſpaſſe, &amp; that it ſhould be lawfull, vnto Prieſts, Biſhops, and Cardinals to commit great and haynous crimes without offence? That Princes ordinances ſhould haue no iuriſdiction ouer them? If they offended that they ſhould make lawes for their own purpoſe? The example pleaſeth me, and verely I thinke it to be ſo altogether, after the ſaying of the Euangeliſt, that we ſhould flollow the wordes but not the workes of thoſe that ſit in the cheare of Moyſes. But hee, Sixtus, that was both God and man, thy better and greater, ſcorned not to appeare before the tribunall ſeate of an earthly Iudge, and being brought into iudgement, complayned not of the Iudge. Iames and Andrewe Apoſtles, and Saint Stephen a Martyr, haue ſubmitted them ſelues
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14615:22"/>vnder the laws, And Saint Paule being impriſoned defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not his libertie by the preeminence of an Apoſtle, but by the title of a Citizen of Rome. But I knowe what thou wilt aunſwere hereupon that Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had not ſo great a libertie, as the Church hath at this day, it is true: Well, ſéeing that the blinde and ignorant ages haue ordained this, let vs beare the burthen which our anceſtors haue layde vpon our ſhoulders, let the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie reioyce in her fréedome, but let them exerciſe their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of offending onely betwéene and vpon themſelues, and let Princes and their ſubiectes be ſafe from their auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and the common wealth voyde of treacherie and ſuch like diueliſh practiſes. If not, heare our lawes and the ſeuere ordinances of our Kinges, who haue exempted alwayes from your priuiledges, publike crymes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of treaſon, and ſuch other like conſpiracies which might turne to the damage of the common wealth. Heare the wordes of thy predeceſſor Innocent. <hi>Qui de Eccleſia aliquem exemerit, vel in ipſa eccleſia, vel loco, vel cultui, Sacerdotibus, &amp; ministris aliquid iniuriae importauerit ad inſtar publici criminis &amp; laeſae Maieſtatis accuſabitur, &amp; conuictus ſeu confeſsus capitali ſententia a Rectoribus prouinciae puniatur.</hi> What doeſt thou anſwere hereupon, art thou not yet conuicted, doeſt thou demande examples to confirme it. Peruſe the monumentes of thy Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and then yéelde ſome reaſon wherefore it be not as lawefull vnto a king to doe the like in his Realme, which was permitted vnto Nicholas the fift in the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Porcarius and Sarra, both famous knightes of Rome, vnto Plus againſt Carrapha and Rebiba Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles, againſt Palian and Alphius noble Earles of Italie, which vnto many other? Whoſe ſteppes are yet to be ſéene in diuerſe places: nay vnto thy ſelfe? that haſt ſéene Rome ſlowing with running ſtreames of bloud, and many Noble mens heads to ſtand vpon poales vppon the gates of the Cittie. But loe yet once I am miſtaken, and nowe the thirde time I confeſſe that thou haſt right.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14615:23"/>
            <p>Without doubt it was a haynous offence for a King to haue puniſhed a Cardinall, although a rebell, a traytor, laying ambuſhes to murther his Prince, tempering poyſon to diſpatch him, heyring villaines to performe the déede. All theſe are purged &amp; quite waſht away with the ſacred oyle of Chriſme, wherewith whoſoeuer is annointed is ſet frée for euer from all authoritie and ſecular power. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſhall haue touched but with his leaſt finger, one ſealed with this noble and worthy caractar, I affirme with thée, that God himſelfe is not able to deliuer him from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But likewiſe grant this vnto me, Sixtus, that all theſe offences, ſlanders, and accuſations, wherewith in great heapes thou chargeſt the king, are contayned and included in the death and execution of both the Guiſes, and this onely excepted, him to be altogether blameleſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: which if thou doſt grant me, I demand of thée like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, wherefore didſt thou not only foretell long before the dolefull kinde of death of this Prince, but didſt wiſh for it. Wherefore calleſt thou <hi>Ioioſa</hi> and <hi>Lenocurtius</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and him of Paris witneſſes of thy vnluckly ſouth-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: what curſe of thée had the poore Prince deſerued, at that time when thou didſt ſée <hi>Ioioſa</hi> and <hi>Lenocurtius?</hi> At that time the Guyſes were not yet executed, Nauarre was not yet ſent for, no truce was made with the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes: for what occaſion then, as a diſmall and filthy Owle didſt thou foreſhow an vnaccuſtomed and ſhamefull end of his life? Did not he proclaime warre againſt the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in the yeare 85? Was not the Guiſe made chiefe of the whole armie, to the ruine, and ouerthrowe of the whole Realme? Were not the Germaine forces diſcomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? what was there omitted? becauſe he would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and be depoſed from his crowne, and goe to priſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not commit the gouernement of his realme vnto the Guyſe, or vnto the Spaniard: onely therefore by a prettie alluſion thou haſt deſtinated him to an extreame puniſhment, as the laſt of his name and family. Thou ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and mocker of our griefe, come hether: wilt thou goe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14615:23"/>about with nightcrowes to mollifie thy words, and hinder with a ſubtil eloquence the deſerued rigor, &amp; puniſhment due to a hainous offence? By theſe means thou defileſt moſt fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely the remembrance of him, whom ſo long for his diſcent, for his worthy actes both done at home and abroade, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinies of this Realme haue aduanced to imperiall dignitie and promotion, and ſo thou requiteſt him with ſlaunders, by whoſe grandfathers and aunceſtors thy ſea hath béene ouercharged and laden with innumerable benefites. Heyda Sixtus, thy aduice pleaſeth mée, and thy witte worthie one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch a high Biſhop as thou art. But here I appeale vnto all theſe Princes that are liuing at this time, and alſo vnto them that ſhall hereafter come to reade theſe our wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that they may acknowledge with mée, the woonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements of the Lorde, and the mockeries and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of fickle fortune. The mightieſt Prince of Europe is murthered: and liue he ſhoulde yet, if long agone he had not noriſhed his bloodſhedders with his owne, and with the blood of the whole realme: and whoſe liues, maners, and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he loued more then his owne welfare, by their fraude, ſword, and treacherie he is depriued of his life. Hee is gone (oh horrible) by their meanes, whoſe ſafetie, when onely he intended, neglected his ſubiects and his owne welfare. And beſides are not yet aſhamed to ſay (but too too bolde) that by their deuiſes the Realme falling to decay, might haue béene repaired and ſupported? His ghoſt is accuſed but by him, whom he hath defended with al carefulnes, being vpon this world, whom he loued moſt dearely, &amp; whom he reuerenced aboue meaſure far more then he was worthie of. The dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful monuments of his loue and loyalty towards thée are yet extant, wherof I would to God that the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce could bee extinguiſhed and quite defaced. To what ende tended ſo many ciuil warres, ſo many maſſacres, ſo many proſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which France hath ſuffered, then onely that thy wealth might remaine vntouched, and all thine might liue in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſecuritie. And yet funeralles, and the laſt home of the body is denied him. Moreouer, from yearely praiers
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14615:24"/>(from whence no enemie euer hath bene barred) he is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and by thoſe at whoſe requeſt we haue ſéene him ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes humblie, but not Princely walke barefoote, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Scepter or Crowne, and his ſworde downewarde. For whoſe dwelling and abiding places he complained that his kingdome was not great enough, for whoſe welfare hée himſelfe hath not onely prayed moſt oftentymes, but hath emoyned vnto his people to doe the like. I will now make an ende in one worde. None coulde méete him that were as welcome vnto him as Friars, none loued the order of Prieſtes more entirely then hee: and of him no body was more eſtéemed of, reuerenced, and honoured then the biſhop of Rome. And vnto him his deſtinies haue procured a friar to be his murtherer, prieſtes his deadly ennemies, and the Pope his accuſer. I craue pardon of thée, O naturall affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if it be lawfull to argue vpon the death of my Prince in a publike griefe) if this be the argument of my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>I will come anone vnto thée Sixtus, when I ſhall bee reſolued of this point: wherefore dooſt thou denie vnto a dead Prince the gift of a little duſt, and comfortable prayers vnto his ſoule? What? Art thou ſo obſtinately angrie and offended with him, as to ſhewe extreme crueltie vppon his aſhes? Leaue his body to be torne at pleaſure vnto thy bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy butchars, let his ſoule enioy at the leaſt eternall reſt: to deſire that both be caſt away, is too vnnaturall, rigorous, and cruell.</p>
            <p>Can the high Biſhoppe not bée appeaſed wyth leſſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes? I demaunde whether this be godlie and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlie ſpoken, O ye Princes of the earth giue eare vnto me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The holy Biſhop of Rome denounceth by Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authority, that he hath opened the gates of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Iames Clement, for to haue murdred the moſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King of France, and that vnto the dead body of the King worthely, the pompe of funeralles, and the honour of buriall may be denied; yea, that leſſe is,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14615:24"/>praiers and ſonges. For to haue denied vnto the Guyſes the goueruement of the Realme at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. Therefore what King ſoeuer, whether he be an Hereticke or Catholicke, if preſently he diſpoſeth not his Crowne at the pleaſure of the high Prieſt, to giue it vnto him, vnto whome it ſhall bee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, let him looke for no better end in this life, and in the life to come. And whoſoeuer ſhall haue op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, by ſword, or poiſon, ſecretly, or ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or by deceit, any Prince, Emperor, or Monarch, not obaying our ſacred thunderbolts. Let him as a ſtarre with a new ſhining light, increaſe the number of the ſtars in the firmament. This is the will of Chriſt his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. The ſucceſſor of S. Peter and S. Paule Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What neede haue wée of thee (O Chriſt) if eternall life can be obtained not by thy bloud, but by that of Kinges and princes, if not by a croſſe, but a knife the way of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is opened vnto Friars.</p>
            <p>Let the ghoſts of Luther and Calum come to hear this, that by theſe ioyful newes and tidings they may eaſe at the leaſt, and mittigate the griefe of their paines if they ſuffer any. But now I come from the footepath vnto the high way againe. It ſéemeth but a matter of nothing vnto Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, to dally with the accuſation of a moſt hainous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, vnder the couller of Gods iudgementes, and vnder a counterfaite and fained authority drawen from the holy Scriptures: but he doth adde examples thereunto, to the end the accurſed traitour might become famous for euer, &amp; not common onely, and of ſuch ſortes of perſons, but by whome the actes of Alexander and Ceſar might bee illuſtrated and commended. I lette paſſe willingly that which hee hath rehearſed of the conception, death, and reſurrection of our Lorde, vngodly to be ſpoken and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to bee hearde. I muſt pauſe a while before I can giue an eare to heare ſuch horrible blaſphemies. Firſt hee prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth Eleazarus his notable acte in ſtabbing the beaſte. Whereupon he thought that Antiochus was, and litle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14615:25"/>his owne life, ſo that he with the fall of the Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, might kill the rider and himſelfe together. He prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the manly audacity and courage of Iudith, not reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting her own welfare and honeſty, ſo that ſhe might with the ennemies head, preſerue the liues, goods, and chaſtity of the Cittizens of Bethulia. Hee extolleth both their zeale, conſtancy, and magnanimity, but ſo as the Poets did He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Aeneas triumphs and victories, that the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour thereby might reape the more praiſe and glory. He commeth preſently vnto his ſonne Clement whom he exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſo hie that he ſeemeth to repent himſelfe to haue produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced theſe vnfit and vnequall examples, and to be angrie that for want of better, hath béene forced to vſe but weake com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons. By theſe meanes let the noble fights and combats of Sampſon and Dauid giue place (Sixtus being iudge) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cain, Ioab, and Iudas their infamous treacheries. Let there be no difference then whether one killeth, villaniouſly or valiantly, a tirant or a king, an enemy or the father of his countrey? Let the Captaines who are famous for their proweſſe, and renowmed through many victories be equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a Friar but crept out of a caue. And finally let the conſtancy of Martirs be commended by the audacity of a murtherer. If this will ſtand for good, why doſt thou not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhe ſtatutes and ordinances, and like as we vſe Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians and Gratians lawes, that we may haue thine alſo Sixtus, to depriue vertue of her due praiſe by them, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their deſerued ſhame and puniſhment: for none are or were euer to be found, that would haue vndertaken the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of this act, thou only excepted. Beſides is not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vſe a common praiſe, but to make the fooliſh people more aſtoniſhed, ſheweth mirakles whereby the deuine po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is argued to haue aſſiſted and furthered this treachery, He telleth therefore how Clement went through the gates of the Citty being ſo narrowly beſieged, and through the watches of both the Camps not marked, or as one ſhould ſay inuiſible, he ſpeaketh this as a wonder, the like whereof Iudith is not able to bring forth, although ſhe be ſo highly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14615:25"/>exalted with ſacred poeſies, that ſhe was a woman, that ſhe had opened her pretence vnto the Magiſtrate &amp; the Elders of the Citie, and that in their companies ſhe went by the Sentinels of the Citie without danger, &amp; then afterwarde was brought before the watch of the enemie, and laſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the chiefe of the armie, and that by the exquiſite beauty of her face ſhe eaſily bewitched the heart and ſenſes of the Prince which were ouercome already with wine and luſt, and that therefore all things were readie &amp; eaſie vnto her. But that all things croſt the Friar, that in euery thing was great trouble and trauell, but yet more daunger, that he alone (ſurely without any bodies helpe or induction) had conceiued ſecretly the boldneſſe of this deſperate enterpriſe. That he had not only to go through the watches of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, but by the Citizens ſtraight wardes &amp; Sentinels: and if his face, his words, or his pace, had bewrayed there any token of vnconſtancie, which oftentimes is ſéene in thoſe that doe attempt high and great matters, he had to looke for nothing, but for preſent death &amp; deſtruction. Here if the letters had béene found about him, he had no leſſe to feare the like of thoſe that were ignorant of the matter and being beſiedged were afeard of euery trifle. So that (as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere ſayth) as Aeneas was carryed by the helpe of Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune out of the battell, euen ſo Sixtus leadeth this Fryar through the Citie, &amp; the Campe couered with a cloud that he could not be ſéene of any body: I maruaile that he hath not ſet him vpon the winges of angels, to carry and bring him in ſafetie to the kinges tente. I appeale vnto your authoritie O honourable and reuerent antiquitie: what is become of ſhamefaſtneſſe? Who thinkes now a dayes a lie to be a diſcredite? Come to heare a hiſtorie &amp; not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Clement by a great ſumme of money, by further hope, &amp; by a notorious harlot was ſolicited, taketh counſell with the chiefe conſpirators of the kings death, and it is knowen now, who were preſent at that inſtant, who were the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, &amp; who were the furtherers. It were iniurious that our poſterity ſhould be deceiued &amp; depriued of the memory of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14615:26"/>this cruell act, and (as I hope cre long) of the example of the execution thereof. They did counterfaite letters from certaine priſonners vnto the King, bewraying ſome great matters to be declared by the mouth of the Fryar, the which when he had receiued, taketh the kniſe which he had made and poyſoned to kill the king withall: and goeth out of the Cittie, but firſt hauing leſt charge that all thoſe that were ſuſpected might be kept within, that by theſe meanes the life of a bloodie murtherer ſhould be in ſafetie with the danger of thouſande innocents, if he ſhould haue fallen a liue in the enemies handes. This is the firſt part of this miracle, theſe are the diuine motions, this is the celeſtiall inſpiration, and this the infallible argument of the preſent aſſiſtance of Gods power. He commeth in the kings campe no man letting him, and at that trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome time, when Fryars onely were frée, and had onely ſafe conduct to goe where they would themſelues. But why goe I about to ſpend my time in confuting Sixtus his lyes, where ſo many blaſphemies doe offer themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me? All theſe are toyes of the common people. Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans vertue ſeparate and diſtinguiſh him from the common ſort: but the Biſhop of Rome let him be knowen by his notorious and extraordinarie villanies. It is an old ſaying, where lawfull things are onely permitted vnto go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, there they command by intreatie, a Prieſt doth not differ from a Lay-man, but onely in libertie of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. It is ſayth hee (ſpeaking of the murthering of the Prince) a moſt famous, and a memorable act, and not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued without the particular prouidence and diſpoſition of the Almightie (pardon me Oeuerlaſting, holy, and omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God, pardon me Opietie, and naturall affection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing wordes which are impious and full of blaſphemie) what Sixtus if thou hadſt onely ſayde that this befell by his permiſſion, vnto whom it is caſie to hinder all thinges, although it be true, it were not godly, and leſſe godly for thée to affirme this that knoweſt not all thinges that are preſent, and therefore the more that thou calleſt in witneſſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14615:26"/>and defence of thy villanyes, him whom thou calleſt good and almightie. <hi>Hei</hi> thou Doctor in Iſraell art thou igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this, that all good things are aſcribed vnto God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that all the reſt is attributed vnto our ſelues? Who can ſuffer then that vnto the ſame God who is good onely, onely omnipotent the bloudie offence of an outcaſt from all man kinde is referred? And yet thou doeſt eſtéeme it but ſmall to ſaye that the King was ſlaine, not onely by thy knowledge, but by thy counſell, not diſſembling at it, but commaunding it, and hauing ſet a ſide all celeſtiall and infernall care, that it hath béene thy will onely and procurement that at thy pleaſure ſuch a haynous and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable murther was committed in France. Doe the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens heare this and ſuffer it? for whom are the gulphes of the earth, the vnluckie rockes, and the fearefull whirlpooles and déepes of hell reſerued? Lightnings and thunderbolts ſhould be wanting if no part of theſe villanies were left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed. Nowe long agone my eares are hardened and acquainted with theſe execrable wordes. And what is all this which I haue ſayde? but vulgar and common, nothing worthie of high Ioue his anger, nothing notorious, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pontificiall. I would willingly follow childrens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions when they are to drinke a medicine: they inuent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, they leaue nothing vndoone, they turne the cup, and oftentimes put it vnto their mouth to taſte it, then they ſhake their heads as if they were angry, they aſke for ſwéet things to ouercome or to mitigate the bitterneſſe of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But finally they being wearied with the continuall cryings of the ſtanders by, turning their head aſide, &amp; ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their noſtrels, do not drinke the medicine but powre it in. The like happeneth vnto me at this time: I would if I might, Sirtus, paſſe by thy horrible blaſphemies &amp; impious wordes, wherewith thou haſt polluted by an abhominable compariſon of a moſt villainous offence, the holy myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Sauiors birth and buriall. I would to God that Chriſtian eares had only hard it, who are déeper grounded in religion &amp; better perſwaded of faith, &amp; who neuer would
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14615:27"/>haue giuen credite to thy impious Dration, if it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to the Barbarians Heathen, and Turkes: who will hereafter make a mocke of the true Chriſtian doctrine, by thy authoritie, Sixtus, and example. Art thou not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that thou, being the Paſtor of the redéemed flocke, by whoſe guiding it draweth the water of life out of the holy well, whoſe wordes ſhould haue ſounded nothing, but that which was ſainct, pure, and godly: that thou the liuely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretor of the written lawe of God, and the ſeuere puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of blaſphemies, and of thoſe that falſefie and corrupt the ſenſe of the holy Scriptures, and moreouer of thoſe that abuſe, or vſe too fréely wordes taken out of the booke of GOD: I will not ſay haſt deluded the Prophetes and Apoſtles, haſt called in doubt the trueth of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, haſt corrupted the holy Scriptures, wreſted and falſefied them by a falſe interpretation, by godly exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples haſt coulloured impious offences, and haſt protected them by thine authoritie, (theſe are but ſmall thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are vſuall vnto thée) but to compare the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall counſell of the redemption of mankinde, which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was committed vnto the ſeconde perſon of the <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> onely of him ſuſcepted, with the vngodly and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable conſpiracie of the murthering of a Prince? And to equall the cafuall audacitie of an imaged and bloudie but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto the reuerende myracles of our Lordes natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, death, and reſurrection? Anoyde impietie, auoyde blaſphemie, infect not the holy Lambe with thy poyſoned breath. What haſt thou left vntouched, whome haſt thou ſpared? what hath not Mahomet nowe to obiect vnto vs? what hath the Iewe any longer to holde his peace? Loc yée Chriſtians: if the Sarriſins, the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the Barbarous people of Calico, inueigh moſt bitterly againſt you, they haue borrowed it of the Biſhoppe of Rome. Diddeſt thou lacke prophane examples, Sixtus, to compare them vnto thy villaynie that thou hadſt a refuge vnto moſt holy and diuine compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons? I am glad, ſir Biſhoppe, that the world hath béene
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14615:27"/>voide vntill thine age of ſuch hainous and publicke mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; that both were reſerued vnto thy time, to wit hee that durſt attempt ſuch a deteſtable acte, and he that was not aſhamed to command it. Come forth all yee, whome the religious antiquity hath ſeperated from the worlde to bee adicted vnto celeſtiall meditations, whome the ſonne neuer ſaw but throwe ſome narrowe riſtes, bring ſhutt vp in high walles and iron doores. Ariſe I ſay and come forth Sixtus calleth you vnto villennie, to the murthering of Kings and princes, now the gates are kept no longer by a ſeuere and frowning porter. And thoſe bars and doores that kept you from the frendly imbraſing of your fathers, and the ſwéete kiſſes of your affectionated mothers, are nowe fréely remoued and opened vnto you, to ſhed by treacherye and treaſon the bloud of your parents, and deareſt frends. I was determined Sixtus, to leaue thy lies, ſurmiſes, and falſe accuſations vntouched: But I am prouoked to the contrarie through thy impudency, which deſerueth no ſmal indignation, as thoſe may eaſely iudge that are ſomewhat acquainted with our eſtat and affaires. Doſt thou ſay that Monkes and Friars were kild, or at the leaſt ill vſed in the Kings Camp? I would to God it had beene ſo, if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and godly to deſire it. But at the leaſt I wiſh that all this idle and vnprofitable cattle ſhould haue béene pounded and impriſoned: then our Prince ſhould liue yet, worthy of a longer life, and then as a fearfull hare thou durſteſt not tread vppon the body of the dead Lion, and deride our griefe and miſhappe. As if all the world knew not that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe ſlaues he neuer was harde, where as oftentimes, he was vnto his moſt familiar friendes ſeuere. Truely his vntimely facillity, hath hurt him, hauing had as yet no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience how much hipocriſie and deceite there lay hidden vnder a Friars hood. As if thy ſelfe didſt not know that hee alwayes had with him two Friers in his armie, whoſe help he alwayes vſed in his diuine ſeruice. Let me be vndon and caſt away, if I would not haue wiſht a Friars wéede, and forſaken my counſellers gowne, if by that meanes I coulde
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14615:28"/>haue perſwaded him to the beſt. Truly none were ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Realm, whoſe welfare and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity, nay not his owne, hée eſteemed not leſſe then theſe peoples delights and pleaſures onely. Thou haſt no lucke, Sixtus, with thy lie, it will not forge, thou mightieſt more eaſier haue made the worlde beleeue any thing els. The enemy himſelfe dare not ſay, that Friars were ill vſed as long as he liued. Here I woulde make an end if I were but certified of one pointe. Reſolue mee, Sixtus, of this, I inquire no further cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the murthered Prince, it ſufficeth mee to knowe that thou haſt commaunded it, thy will ſhall ſtande for a lawe. But wherefore doſt thou perſecute his ſhadowe, wherefore doeſt thou accuſe him of obſtinacy, impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? vnthankefulneſſe, and to haue ſinned againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt? Why doeſt thou compare him with Cain and Iudas? By what iuſtice or equitie canſt thou doe this? when hee lay vppon his death bedde did hee doubt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith? Did hee deny the euerlaſting Sonne of the eternall GOD? Hath hee neglected the auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of the Church, and the moſt comfortable Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vnto thoſe that he in their extremity? Yet once againe herein thou art a notable lier. Why doſt thou force mee ſo oftentimes to repeate the remembraunce of my bitter griefes? It is certaine that the godly Prince, as ſoone as the Phiſitions and Surgeons had bounde vp his wounde and had laide him vppon his bedde, hauing a little ſlepte vppon his paine and griefe, that hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced with his owne mouth his Prayers, and with a loude voice, made confeſſion of his faith, and of the feeling which hee had of his redemption: adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto theſe wordes vnto GOD. If it bee to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, O GOD, and the commoditie of my people, graunte mee I moſt humbly deſire, firſt pardon for my ſinnes, and then ſome longer dayes of life. But if it bee otherwiſe, I thanke thee moſt highly, O Father, that thou doeſt barre mee hence forth from the thraldome of ſinne, whereby wee moſte oftentimes procure thy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14615:28"/>wrath againſt vs. And therefore I am readie moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come where thou calleſt me. Hauing made an ende of his Prayers he ſendeth for his brother the King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre, and for the chiefeſt of his army, and vnto his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he commendeth the charge of the Realme, and the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of his ſubiects, the Lawes of France, importing as much: and repeted oftentimes theſe words, whereby he charged him to haue a ſpeciall care to kéepe Chriſtes flocks in vnity and concord: and as he was heire vnto the crowne, that he likewiſe would be heire to godly and ancient inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Deſiring this moſt earneſtly at his hands with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhewing that this had bin his only deſire from his childhood. They al depart very ſorrowful, whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he confeſſeth his ſins in the eare of a prieſt, &amp; hauing craued pardon of God for his offences, he had a ſenſible féeling, that they were forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for Chriſts ſake. And nowe ready to communicate of his ſacred body openly that al might hears it, that grace which he had fréely receiued of God in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of his ſins, that ſame he frankly imparteth to al his enemies, nay to them that had béene the conſpirators of his death, &amp; his murtherers. And thus hauing receiued his laſt due &amp; farewell, departed ioyful &amp; glad out of this worlde, not without the great griefe of all the ſtanders by, bewraying y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward ſorrowe with outward abundant teares. Here Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, I ſée no tokens of deſperation, no ſignes of impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. And I thinke not, that thou art ſo farre voyde of al rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as to compare a moſt Chriſtian prince vnto K. Saule. But let him be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared yet to him, ſo that he heare no bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer words, &amp; ſuffer greater torments. Beholde with what words Gods indignation vpon this impious king is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The ſpirite of the Lorde is gone from Saule, ſaith the prophet: And in another place the Lord ſpeaketh vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, ſaying, How long wilt thou lament ouer Saul, when I haue caſt him off that he ſhall not raigne? Doth he ſaie, that he is miſerable, vnhappie, &amp; worthy of eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? God forbid. When the ſcripture ſpeaketh of his death, marke the moſt chriſtian wordes of Dauid, directed vnto
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14615:29"/>the vnluckie yongman, who boaſted, but falſely, that hee; with his owne handes had ſlaine the Prince in the battell: How waſt thou not afraid to put forth thy hand, to deſtroy the annointed of the Lord? And in many other places, who ſhall ſtretch forth his hands vpon the Lords annointed, and ſhall be innocent? Anſwere Sixtus, is not thy oration cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eller whereby thou commaundeſt wilfull and publike mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in praiſnig it: or ſay, that this example is not to be fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and to be aboliſhed by thine authoritie. Saule was ſlaine in the battell, an Amalekite his enemy had doone it, here is nothing that was forbidden by lawe, yet the Lorde hath reuenged the death of his annointed. Sée further what the holy Chronicles tell of Ioab, and Ammon, being mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, although vngodly kings, authors of abhominations, and hated of God. Sée, reade, and peruſe all the ſacred and prophane hiſtories, and thou ſhalt finde, that not onely the lawe of nature, of men, and aboue all Gods ordinances, but alſo the ſeuere and horrible examples of the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, debarre impious and bloodie handes, from the annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bodies of kings and Princes. Rome fertile alwayes in all villanie, hath féene of twelue her Emperors, eight mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered wyth the ſword, but none vnreuenged. He, Sixtus, therefore that ſuccéedeth ſhall be, I hope, the reuenger, and that which thou haſt now long agone knowne by other hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, thou ſhalt come to learne it ere long by thine owne. Auoyde therefore, thou Biſhop, and be prowde with this anſwere: Go vnto the Indians, or in ſome other cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the world, a iuſt puniſhment is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for thée vnder ſome greater ennemy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14615:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
